<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A supplement to The queen-like closet, or, A little of everything presented to all ingenious ladies, and gentlewomen / by Hannah Woolley ...</title>
            <author>Woolley, Hannah, fl. 1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 231 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 110 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221176</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475293</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475293</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151469</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96816)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151469)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2260:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A supplement to The queen-like closet, or, A little of everything presented to all ingenious ladies, and gentlewomen / by Hannah Woolley ...</title>
                  <author>Woolley, Hannah, fl. 1670.</author>
                  <author>Woolley, Hannah, fl. 1670. Queen-like closet.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 200 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. for Richard Lownds, and are to be Sold at the Sign of the White Lion ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound and stained, with print show-through and some loss of print; p. 21-22, 55-56, 65-66 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cookery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Home economics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151469:1"/>
            <p>A SUPPLEMENT TO THE <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN-LIKE</hi> CLOSET;</p>
            <p>OR A LITTLE OF EVERY THING.</p>
            <p>PRESENTED To all Ingenious Ladies, and Gentlewomen.</p>
            <p>By <hi>HANNA WOOLLEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> for <hi>Richard Lownds,</hi> and are to be Sold at the Sign of the <hi>White Lion</hi> in <hi>Duck-Lane,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:151469:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151469:2"/>
            <head>To all Ingenious Ladies and Gentlewomen.</head>
            <l>LADIES, The last I ſent unto your view,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>The Queen-like Cloſet</hi> I preſented you:</l>
            <l>And in it ſuch rare Secrets, I may ſay,</l>
            <l>In no Book you will find (though read you may)</l>
            <l>The twelve years past ſince first in print I came</l>
            <l>More for my Countries good, than to get fame.</l>
            <l>My study was to impart to others free,</l>
            <l>What God and Nature hath informed me.</l>
            <l>I must not hide that Talent God me gave,</l>
            <l>Content I am others a ſhare ſhould have</l>
            <l>To practice what I teach; if pains they'l take,</l>
            <l>Amends for all my Care they will me make.</l>
            <l>Servant to Ingenuity I'le be,</l>
            <l>Such <hi>Ladies</hi> ſhall command all Arts from me.</l>
            <l>Nothing from them I'le hide, that's in my heart,</l>
            <l>To wait on them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I think it is my part.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:151469:3"/>
            <l> And to confirm to them what I have writ,</l>
            <l>Fearing no Cenſures, mongst them that have Wit.</l>
            <l>If any one that Honour will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e give,</l>
            <l>To ſee me in the place where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do live,</l>
            <l>I will them ſatisfie in every thing</l>
            <l>That they deſire, and vindication bring</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto my ſelf, who have been much abus'd</l>
            <l>By a late printe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Book, my Name there us'd:</l>
            <l>I was far distant when they printed it,</l>
            <l>Therefore that book to even I think not ſit.</l>
            <l>To boast, to brag, tell stories in my praiſe,</l>
            <l>That's not the way (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> know) my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame to raiſe;</l>
            <l>Nor ſhall I borrow thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or Wit</l>
            <l>(Innocence will hide what fault<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I do commit.)</l>
            <l>My true intent is, for to ſerve you all;</l>
            <l>To Works to Write, to Come when you do call,</l>
            <l>Nor would I ſeem as dead while I do live<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>No commendation to me would that give:</l>
            <l>Nor like the idle Drone my time to paſs,</l>
            <l>But as the <hi>Bee,</hi> ſuck Hony from Flower and Graſs.</l>
            <l>The Quinteſcence of what I have I ſend;</l>
            <l>Accept it really, as I intend,</l>
            <l>For to accompliſh thoſe who want the skill,</l>
            <l>Their Tables to adorn and Cloſets fill.</l>
            <l>To thoſe of riper Judgment I ſubmit,</l>
            <l>To commend, or to conſure what I've writ.</l>
            <l>Thus <hi>Ladies,</hi> I take leave, deſiring still,</l>
            <l>Your pleaſures and your fancies to fulfil.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151469:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU find in my former Books Inſtructions, for <hi>Cookery, Preſerving,</hi> Rare <hi>Waters,</hi> both Cordial and pleaſant; <hi>Cakes, Jellies;</hi> ſeveral excellent Remedies for thoſe in <hi>Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and for the <hi>Stone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now give you ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for waſhing Black, and White <hi>Sarſnets,</hi> or Coloured <hi>Silks;</hi> waſhing of <hi>Points, Laces,</hi> or the like; ſtarching of <hi>Tiffanies,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king clean <hi>Plate,</hi> cleaning of <hi>Gold</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:151469:4"/> and <hi>Silver Lace,</hi> waſhing <hi>Silk Stockings,</hi> adorning of <hi>Cloſets</hi> with ſeveral pretty Fancies; things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent to keep the <hi>Hands</hi> white, and <hi>Face</hi> and <hi>Eyes</hi> clear; how to make <hi>Tranſparent Work,</hi> and the <hi>Colours</hi> thereto belonging; alſo <hi>Puff Work:</hi> Some more Receipts for <hi>Preſerving</hi> and <hi>Cookery:</hi> Some Remedies for ſuch <hi>Ailments</hi> as are incident to all People; as <hi>Corns, Sore Eyes, Cut Fingers, Bruiſes, Bleeding at Noſe;</hi> all theſe you may help, by my Directions, with a ſmall matter of Coſt; whereas elſe, you may be at a great Charge and long Trouble, and perhaps endanger your <hi>Eyes,</hi> or <hi>Limbs.</hi> I ſhall give you none, but ſuch things as I have had many years Experience of, with good ſucceſs, I praiſe God.</p>
            <p>As you dare conſide in me, I pray make uſe of them: I hope you will not fear, ſince what I
<pb facs="tcp:151469:4"/> have already imparted hath been found true, and hath benefited many.</p>
            <p>Some are of that mind, that they value nothing but what is, <hi>Far fetcht, Dear bought,</hi> or <hi>Hard to be had,</hi> and will rather prize thoſe things which are kept Secret, though if known, are but ſimple: And ſuch are apt to ſlight what is made known to them, not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>reality</hi> of the Friend who doth impart it to them, meerly out of their Good-will, and to ſave their Purſes. Such is the <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of this wicked World, that whatſoever one doth out of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and Chriſtian-like mind; yet it is ſlighted. I may compare it to thoſe words in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which ſays, <hi>Caſt not Pearl before Swine.</hi> And, if <hi>Gallen,</hi> and <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> and <hi>Paracelſus</hi> were alive, or any of the Wiſeſt Philoſophers, and ſhould declare in Writing all
<pb facs="tcp:151469:5"/> their Skill, and lay thoſe Writings down to the view of every Eye, not one in ten would believe it. For my part, I am of that mind, never to condemn any Man till I prove it falſe; nor publickly to commend any thing, till I find it good. You may believe me, if you pleaſe, and as you find the Truth, ſo truſt me.</p>
            <p>I have been <hi>Phyſician</hi> and <hi>Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> in my own Houſe to many and alſo to many of my Neighbours, eight or ten Miles round. I think it not amiſs to recite ſome of thoſe Cures I have done, the Places where I have done them, and upon whom; but cannot particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly tell you with what, where the Cure is difficult; becauſe there is in thoſe caſes a good Judgment required; and I uſe thoſe things in thoſe Caſes which are not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Receipts, which may as wel Kill, as Cure; but ſuch things as I
<pb facs="tcp:151469:5"/> find proper to take away the Cauſe of the Diſtemper; Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience with much Reading muſt give that underſtanding. I dare not therefore adventure to teach, but only thoſe things wherein People cannot eaſily Erre, and by which they may receive good.</p>
            <p>For the reſt of what I have ſpoken, and for many other things which I cannot in few words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, if any Perſon will come to me, I will ſatisfie them to their content; and be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Their Friend, and Servant,</hi> H. Woolley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:151469:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151469:6"/>
            <head>The TABLE, OR CONTENTS of this BOOK.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>FOR any <hi>Ague</hi> whatever. page 18</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>A Moſt excellent <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom</hi> for wounds, p. 20</item>
               <item>For pain in the <hi>Bones,</hi> 23</item>
               <item>For <hi>biting</hi> of a Mad-dog, 29</item>
               <item>To ſtench <hi>bleeding,</hi> 35</item>
               <item>For the <hi>Bloody Flux,</hi> 36</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Black-ſalve</hi> ſo Corns, 37</item>
               <item>An excellent <hi>Balſom,</hi> 40</item>
               <item>For a <hi>Bruiſe,</hi> 45</item>
               <item>For a <hi>Burn,</hi> 46</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Botch</hi> or <hi>Boyl,</hi> 56</item>
               <item>To Dye <hi>black,</hi> 67</item>
               <item>To <hi>boil Beef</hi> or <hi>Mutton</hi> to eat ſavourly, 87</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beef-Pye,</hi> 91</item>
               <item>To dreſs old <hi>Beans,</hi> or <hi>French Beans,</hi> 96</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beef</hi> ſtewed. 97</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bisket,</hi> 105</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>FOr a <hi>Cancer</hi> in the Breaſt, or for ſore Eyes, <hi>p.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>For a <hi>Cow</hi> that ſtales bloud, 24</item>
               <item>To make Oil of <hi>Charity,</hi> 29</item>
               <item>A <hi>Cordial Electuary,</hi> 36</item>
               <item>Water for a <hi>Canker,</hi> 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſumption,</hi> 46</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 51</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 55</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colours</hi> for Puff-work, 66</item>
               <item>More <hi>Colours. p.</hi> 67</item>
               <item>To fry <hi>Clary,</hi> 83</item>
               <item>To boil a <hi>Cock</hi> with broth, 88</item>
               <item>A <hi>Calves head</hi> Pye, 97</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chilblanes</hi> on the hands 52</item>
               <item>To <hi>Candy</hi> white Sugar, 110</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Catarrhs,</hi> and <hi>Conſumption,</hi> 112</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Catholick</hi> Plaiſter, 111</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cordial</hi> Electualy, 121</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cordial</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, 122</item>
               <item>To <hi>Candy</hi> Fruit, 126</item>
               <item>To d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs up a <hi>Chimney,</hi> 127. 129</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>TO Cure a <hi>Deafneſs p.</hi> 27</item>
               <item>A <hi>Diet-drink,</hi> 31</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drink</hi> for a Cough, and o-ther Diſtempers, 41</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Deafneſs,</hi> 49</item>
               <item>A <hi>Drink</hi> to comfort you, 121</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>EMorroids</hi> or <hi>Piles, p.</hi> 59</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>TO waſh the <hi>Face, p.</hi> 9</item>
               <item>For the <hi>Falling ſickneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 18</item>
               <item>For any ſpots in the <hi>face,</hi> 22</item>
               <item>For a <hi>film</hi> in the Eye, 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Faces</hi> ſcabbed, 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Frames</hi> for Pictures, 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Feathers</hi> of Wooſted, 73</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fruits</hi> preſerved, 108</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:151469:7"/>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>FOr the cold <hi>Gout.</hi> hot <hi>Gout, p</hi> 25 25</item>
               <item>A <hi>Glister</hi> to cool and bind, 26</item>
               <item>The running <hi>Gout,</hi> or any hot Tumor, 27</item>
               <item>Plaiſter for the <hi>Gout,</hi> 28</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Glaſt</hi> windows made clean, 68</item>
               <item>To <hi>gild</hi> any thing with <hi>gold</hi> or <hi>ſilver,</hi> 126</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>TO keep the <hi>Hair</hi> clean, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſerve it, <hi>p.</hi> 8</item>
               <item>Rheum falling from the <hi>head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 19</item>
               <item>To cure a <hi>Horſe</hi> of a Cold, 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Huckle-bone,</hi> 47</item>
               <item>Pain in the <hi>head,</hi> 48</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Heart-burning,</hi> 50</item>
               <item>Paſſion of the <hi>heart,</hi> 50</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hangings</hi> for Cloſers, 72</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>FOr the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, p.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Impoſtame</hi> in the Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 48</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſo Ague or Feavor, 59</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jelly</hi> for a weak ſtomach 109</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jelly</hi> of Fruits, 116</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K</head>
               <item>FOr <hi>Kbed-heels, p.</hi> 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kings Evil,</hi> 55<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 56</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>TO make clean <hi>gold</hi> and <hi>ſilver Lace, p.</hi> 7</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Lip ſalve,</hi> 9</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 23</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 119</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>MAdneſe</hi> and <hi>fumes</hi> in the Head, 23</item>
               <item>Falling down of the <hi>Mother,</hi> 28</item>
               <item>To dreſs <hi>Mutton</hi> very ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourly. 89</item>
               <item>To ſtew <hi>Muſcles</hi> or <hi>Cockles,</hi> 90</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marmalade</hi> of Damſons, 118</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marmalade</hi> with Barberſies and Pippins, 124</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>TO Cure ſore <hi>Nipples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Numlneſs</hi> in Lambs, 48</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Neats Tongues</hi> ported, 86</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>A Moſt excellent <hi>Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, p.</hi> 19</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Obſtructions,</hi> 113</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>TO make clean <hi>Points,</hi> or <hi>Laces, p.</hi> 3</item>
               <item>To waſh and ſtarch <hi>Points,</hi> 3</item>
               <item>To make clean <hi>Plate,</hi> 8</item>
               <item>To Cure one who <hi>piſſeth</hi> their Bed, 22</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Poultis</hi> for any Sore, 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pin</hi> and <hi>Web</hi> in the Eye, 43</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plague</hi> Sore, 57</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plague</hi> and <hi>Peſtilence, ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Puff work,</hi> 64</item>
               <item>To make the <hi>Puffs,</hi> 65</item>
               <item>To acorn a Room with <hi>Prints,</hi> 70</item>
               <item>To d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs up <hi>Gloſs plates,</hi> 72</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Petticoats, Bodice</hi> or <hi>Belts</hi> embroidered, 81</item>
               <item>To <hi>Pot</hi> Fowls. 85</item>
               <item>To ſtew <hi>Parſnips,</hi> 90</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pigeon</hi> Pye, very good, 92</item>
               <item>Loyn of <hi>Pork</hi> boiled, 93</item>
               <item>To b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll green <hi>Peaſe,</hi> 95</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:151469:7"/>
               <item>To <hi>preſerve</hi> Green <hi>Peaſe</hi> a while, <hi>p.</hi> 95</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pudding</hi> of cold Meat, 98</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paſte,</hi> very rich and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, 120</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>TO kill <hi>Rats, p.</hi> 23</item>
               <item>For <hi>Rheum</hi> in the Eyes, 34</item>
               <item>For the <hi>Rickets</hi> in Children, 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rheum</hi> and <hi>Cough,</hi> 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Red-face.</hi> 54</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Red Beets</hi> dreſſed well, 92</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rabbits</hi> ſtewed, 94</item>
               <item>Sirrop of <hi>Roſes,</hi> 107</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>SWeet-meat</hi> of Grapes, 123</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sirrop</hi> of Snails, 118</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sweetmeat</hi> of Lettuce-ſtalks, 117</item>
               <item>To waſh white <hi>Sarſnets,</hi> 4</item>
               <item>To waſh black <hi>Sarſnets, Silk-ſtockings,</hi> and coloured <hi>Silks,</hi> 6</item>
               <item>To ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>spots</hi> of Ink out of any linnen Cloth. 7</item>
               <item>Likewiſe, <hi>ſtains</hi> of Fruit, 7</item>
               <item>Alſo, greaſie <hi>spots</hi> out of Silk, Stuff or Cloth, 8</item>
               <item>For the <hi>Stone</hi> and <hi>Choller,</hi> 32</item>
               <item>For the <hi>Stone,</hi> 36</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sinew-ſtrain,</hi> 45</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Shingles,</hi> 47</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scabbed head,</hi> 51</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scurvy,</hi> 53</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Squinancy</hi> or <hi>Sore-throas,</hi> 54</item>
               <item>To <hi>ſtain Satten,</hi> 66</item>
               <item>To <hi>ſtarch Tiffany,</hi> 1</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>TO keep the <hi>Teeth</hi> clean and ſound. <hi>p.</hi> 10</item>
               <item>To cure a <hi>Timpany,</hi> 30</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thiſtolow water,</hi> 31, 33</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tooth-ach,</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thruſh</hi> in the mouth, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Transparent work,</hi> 62</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colours</hi> for it, <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>More <hi>Colours</hi> for it, 63 64</item>
               <item>A <hi>Toy</hi> to catch Flies, 125</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>TO ſtew <hi>Veal</hi> ſavourly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>p.</hi> 88</item>
               <item>Sirrop of <hi>Violets,</hi> 106</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W</head>
               <item>FOr <hi>VVorms,</hi> a miraculous Cure, <hi>p.</hi> 19</item>
               <item>For <hi>Worms</hi> in Children, 57</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Worms</hi> in the Noſe, 58</item>
               <item>in the Cheſt, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Work</hi> for Chairs, 77, 78</item>
               <item>To make <hi>Wax<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>work,</hi> 182</item>
               <item>To make the <hi>moulds</hi> for it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 184</item>
               <item>To make the likeneſs of many things in <hi>Wax,</hi> without the help of a Mould, 185</item>
               <item>To take the ſhape of your own <hi>hand,</hi> 186</item>
               <item>To take the <hi>face</hi> of a dead Body, 187</item>
               <item>For <hi>Eggs</hi> to be hard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and cut in quarters, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colours</hi> for <hi>Wax-work,</hi> 189, 190, 191</item>
               <item>To make <hi>Spaniſh white,</hi> 192</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:151469:8"/>
               <head>LETTERS<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </head>
               <item>FRom a <hi>Siſter</hi> to a <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> far diſtant from her, <hi>pag</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Daughter</hi> to he <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 150</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Mother</hi> to a <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter</hi> in a <hi>Ladies</hi> Service, 151</item>
               <item>The Anſwer. 152</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Siſter</hi> to a <hi>Brother,</hi> 153</item>
               <item>From one Friend to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, 158</item>
               <item>The Anſwer, 156</item>
               <item>From one Siſter to another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 156</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Lady</hi> to a <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman,</hi> whom ſhe hath a Kindneſs for, 157</item>
               <item>The Anſwer, 155</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Wife</hi> to her <hi>Husband,</hi> craving his pardon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 160</item>
               <item>From an <hi>Aunt</hi> to her <hi>Neece,</hi> 161</item>
               <item>The Anſwer, 162</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Widow</hi> to her <hi>Friend,</hi> deſiring her Aſſiſtance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 163</item>
               <item>The Anſwer, 164</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Woman</hi> in Priſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o her <hi>Friend</hi> to help her, 165</item>
               <item>The Anſwer, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>From a <hi>Seamans Wife</hi> to her <hi>Husband,</hi> 166</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Servant</hi> to her <hi>Miſtriſs,</hi> concerning her Charge, 166</item>
               <item>A Letter of Complement from one Friend to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, 167</item>
               <item>The Anſwer, 168</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Mother</hi> to a <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> who had gone aſtray from her, 169</item>
               <item>The <hi>Daughters</hi> Anſwer to her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Mother.</hi> 170</item>
               <item>A Letter from a <hi>Gentleman</hi> to a Rela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of his, <hi>&amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 172</item>
               <item>The <hi>Ladies</hi> Anſwer, 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>From a <hi>Gentlewoman</hi> to her <hi>Father,</hi> 175</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Gentlewoman</hi> to her <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 176</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Widow</hi> to her <hi>Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord.</hi> 177</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Gentlewoman</hi> to her <hi>Brother</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 177</item>
               <item>From a <hi>Gentlewoman</hi> in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter from a <hi>Gentleman</hi> who Courted her. 178</item>
               <item>Another Letter from a <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman,</hi> to one who Courted her for his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, 181</item>
               <item>The Cauſe why good Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or the Children of worthy Parents, are off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in a diſtreſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, 135</item>
               <item>The Cauſe why others do commonly run into miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and wickedneſs, 138</item>
               <item>Advice to Parents concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Children, and Advice to Children con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Parents, 141</item>
               <item>Directions for the more cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious working and adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Images</hi> of the <hi>Poetical Gods</hi> and <hi>Goddeſies, p.</hi> 193, 194, 195, 196</item>
               <item>Alſo for the better Drawing of the <hi>Months</hi> of the Year, 197, 198, 199</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:151469:8"/>
            <head>AN Advertiſment.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IF any Perſon deſire to ſpeak with me, they may find me at Mr.</hi> Richard Wolleys <hi>Houſe in the</hi> Old-Baily <hi>in</hi> Golden Cup <hi>Court; He is Maſter of Arts, and Reader at St.</hi> Martins Ludgate. <hi>They may have of me ſeveral Remedies for ſeveral Diſtempers, at reaſonable Rates. Likewiſe, If any Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, or other Maids, who deſire to go forth to Service, and do want Accompliſhment for the ſame: For a reaſonable Gratuity I ſhall inform them</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151469:9"/>
            <p>ſtone, and keep them all the time from the Air, for that will ſpoil them.</p>
            <p>Then make your ſtarch of a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thickneſs, and blew it according to your liking, and to a quarter of a pound of Starch, put as much Allom as an Haſel Nut; boyl it very well and ſtrain it, and while it is hot, wet your Tiffanies with it very well, and lay them in a Cloth to keep them from drying, then waſh your hands clean and dry them, then hold your Tiffanies to a good fire till they be through hot, then clap them and rub them between your hands from the fire till you ſee they be very clear, then ſhape them by a piece of Paper cut out by them before they were waſhed, and iron them with a good hot Iron, and then they will look gloſſie like new Tiffany.</p>
            <p>Thus you may ſtarch Lawns; but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to iron them on the wrong ſide, and upon a Cloth wetted and wrung out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Sometimes (if you pleaſe) inſtead of Starch you may lay Gum-Arabick in water, and when it is diſſolved, wet your Lawns in that inſtead of Starch, and hold them to the fire as before directed, clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them and rubbing them till they are very cleer.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151469:9"/>
               <head>To make clean Points or Laces.</head>
               <p>Take white Bread of half a day old, and cut it in the middle, and pare the Cruſt round the edge, ſo that you may not hurt your Points when you rub them, then lay them on a Table upon a clean Cloth, and rub them very well with the white Bread all over, then take a clean little bruſh and rub over the Bread very well, till you think you have rubbed it very clean, then take your Point or Lace and ſhake the Bread clean off; then bruſh it very well from the Bread, and take a clean linnen Cloth and gently flap it over oft-times.</p>
               <p>Thus you may get the ſoil off from white Satten, Tabby, Taffety, or any Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured Silk; provided it be not greazy nor too much ſoiled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To waſh and ſtarch Points.</head>
               <p>Take your Points and put them into a tent, then make a ſtrong ladder with the beſt Soap you can get; then dip a bruſh in that ladder and ſoundly rub your Point on both ſides; ſo do till you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151469:10"/> have waſhed it in four ladders, then waſh it in fair water alone, then with blew water; and when you have ſo done, take Starch made thin with Water, and with your bruſh on the wrong ſide waſh it over with it, ſo let it dry: then lay your tent upon a Table, and with an Ivory bodkin made for the purpoſe run into every cloſe and narrow part of it, to open it betwixt the gimp or over-caſt; likewiſe into every Ilet hole to open them.</p>
               <p>For the Laces after you have pulled them out well with your hands, you muſt iron them on the wrong ſide.</p>
               <p>Let your water be warm wherewith you make your ladder.</p>
               <p>When you take them out of the tent, iron them on the wrong ſide: let not the water be too blew with which you waſh them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To waſh White Sarſnets.</head>
               <p>Lay them very ſmooth and ſtreight upon a Board, and if there be any dirty plats ſoap them a little, then take a little hard bruſh and ſoap it well, then dip that bruſh in water, and with it make a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thick ladder, then take the bruſh and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151469:10"/> rub your Sarſnet well, the right way of the Sarſnet ſide-waies of the bruſh, and when you have waſhed one ſide well, turn it and waſh the other.</p>
               <p>Then have a clean ladder ſcalding hot, and caſt your Hoods in double into it, and cover it, and ſtill as faſt as you waſh them caſt them into that; you muſt give them three good waſhes upon the board, and after the firſt ladder let the other be very hot, and caſt them in a ſcald every time, then make up a ſcalding hot ladder, into which put ſome Gum-Arabick, ſteeped before in water, and ſome ſmalt to blew it a little, let them lie doubled up in that, cloſe covered for one hour; when you come to take them out, be ſure you dip them very well all over, and then fold them up to a very little compaſs, and ſqueeze them ſmooth betwixt your hands, then ſmoak them over Brimſtone, then draw them between your hands e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way till they be little more than half dry, then ſmooth them with good hot Irons the ſame way you did waſh them, and upon the right ſide of the Sirſnet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151469:11"/>
               <head>To waſh Coloured Silk.</head>
               <p>They are done the ſame way with the White, only there muſt be no blew, nor ſmoaking over brimſtone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To waſh Black Sarſnets.</head>
               <p>They are waſhed the very ſame way with the other, only wrinſed in ſtrong Beer cold, without any Gum, and iron'd upon the wrong ſide, and on a woollen Cloth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To waſh Silk Stockings.</head>
               <p>Make a good ſtrong ladder with Soap, and pretty hot, then lay your ſtockings on a Table, and take a piece of ſuch Cloth as the Sea-men uſes for their Sails, double it up and rub them ſoundly with it; turn them firſt on one ſide, and then on the other till they have paſt through three ladders, then wrinſe them well, and hang them to dry with the wrong ſides outward; and when they are near dry, pluck them out with your hands, and ſmooth them with an Iron on the wrong ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151469:11"/>
               <head>To make clean Gold and Silver Lace.</head>
               <p>Take the Lace off from your garment, and lay it upon a Table, and with a bruſh rub it all over very well with burnt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom heaten fine, till you find it to become of the right colour, then ſhake it very well, and wipe it very well with a clean linnen Cloth often times over.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To get ſpots of Ink out of any linnen Cloth.</head>
               <p>Before that you ſuffer it to be waſhed, lay it all night in Urine, the next day rub all the ſpots in the Urine, as if you were waſhing in water, then lay it in more U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine another night, and then rub it again, and ſo do till you find they be quite out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To get the ſtains of Fruit out of any linnen Cloth.</head>
               <p>Take them before they are waſhed, and with a little Butter rub every ſpot very well, then let the Cloth lye in ſcalding-hot Milk a while, and when it is a little cooled, rub the ſpotted places in the Milk till you ſee they are quite out, and then waſh it in Water and Soap.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151469:12"/>
               <head>To take out any greaſie ſpots out of Silk, Stuff, or Cloth.</head>
               <p>Take a linnen rag and wet it very well in fair water, then with a pair of tongs put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> live Sea-coal or Wood-coal up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wet rag, and haſtily cloſe the reſt of the rag about the coal, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently lay it upon the greaſie ſpot while it is ſmoaking hot; and when you do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to be cool do ſo again, and ſo do till you find they are quite taken out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make clean Plate.</head>
               <p>Waſh your Plate firſt in Soap-ſuds and dry it, then if there be any ſpots, rub them out with Salt and Vinegar.</p>
               <p>Then when you have ſo done anoint your Plate all over with Vinegar and Chalk, and lay it in the Sun or before the fire to dry, then rub it off with warm clean linnen Cloths very well, and it will look like new.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To keep the Hair clean, and to preſerve it.</head>
               <p>Take two handfuls of Roſemary, and boil it ſoftly in a quart of Spring-water till it comes to a pint, and let it be cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151469:12"/> all the while, then ſtrain it out and keep it; every Morning when you Comb your head, dip a ſponge in this water and rub up your Hair, and it will keep it clean and preſerve it, for it is very good for the brain, and will dry up Rheum.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To waſh the Face.</head>
               <p>There is no better thing to waſh the face with, to keep it ſmooth and to ſcour it clean, than to waſh it every night with Brandy, wherein you have ſteeped a little flower of Brimſtone, and the next day wipe it only with a Cloth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a Salve for the Lips.</head>
               <p>Take two ounces of white Bees-wax and ſlice it thin, then melt it over the fire with 2 ounces or more of pure, ſallad Oyl and a little white Sugar Candy, and when you ſee that it is well incorporated take it off the fire, and let it ſtand till it be cold. Then ſet the skillet on the fire again till the bottom is warm, and ſo turn it out; anoint your Lips or ſore Noſe, or ſore Nipples with this, and it will heal.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151469:13"/>
               <head>To keep the Teeth clean and ſound.</head>
               <p>Take common white Salt one ounce, as much of Cuttle-bone beat, them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and rub your Teeth with it every Morning, and then waſh them with fair water.</p>
               <p>I have ſpoken enough concerning your Cloaths, and Face and Hands; now I vvill give you direction for to be your own Chirurgions and Phyſicians, unleſs the caſe be deſperate: but before I begin to teach, be pleaſed to take notice of vvhat Cures I have done, that you may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of my ability.</p>
               <p>FIrſt, Take notice that my Mother and my Elder Siſters vvere very vvell skilled in Phyſick and Chirurgery, from vvhom I learned a little, and at the age of ſeventeen I had the fortune to belong to a Noble Lady in this Kingdom, till I Married, which was at twenty four years (thoſe ſeven-years I was with her) ſhe finding my genius, and being of a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable temper to do good amongſt her poor Neighbours, I had her purſe at command to buy what Ingredients might
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151469:13"/> be required to make Balſoms, Salves, Oyntments, Waters for Wounds, Oyls, Cordials and the like; beſides ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured ſuch knowledge for me from her Phyſicians and Chirurgions (who were the beſt that all <hi>England</hi> could afford) and alſo bought many Books for me to read, that in ſhort time, with the help of thoſe Worthy men before mentioned, I ſoon became a Practitioner, and did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with Cut fingers, Bruiſes, Aches, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, Head-ach, Bleeding at the Noſe, Felons, Whitloes on the Fingers, Sore Eyes, Drawing of Bliſters, Burnings, Tooth-ach, and any thing which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly incident; and in all thoſe Cures God was pleaſed to give me good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
               <p>When I was about the age of two and twenty years, I was ſent by this Noble Lady to a Woman in hard labour of Child, who being quite wearied out with her pains, ſhe fell into ſtrong Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion fits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which greatly endangered both her ſelf and her Child; but by Gods help thoſe Remedies which I gave her cauſed her Fits to ceaſe, and a ſafe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery followed.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:151469:14"/>
               <p> When I was Married to Mr. <hi>Wolley,</hi> we lived together at <hi>Newport Pond</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> near <hi>Saffron Walden</hi> ſeven years; my Husband having been Maſter of that Free-School fourteen years before; we having many Boarders my skill was often exerciſed amongſt them, for oftentimes they got miſhaps when they were play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and oftentimes fell into diſtempers; as Agues, Feavors, Meazles, Small-pox, Conſumptions, and many other Diſeaſes; in all which, unleſs they were deſperately ill, their Parents truſted me without the help of any Phyſician or Chirurgion: likewiſe the Neighbours in eight or ten miles round came to me for Cure.</p>
               <p>A Woman vvho had had a ſore Leg one and twenty years I quite Cured.</p>
               <p>Another being kicked by a Churliſh Husband on her Leg, ſo that a Vein vvas burſt, whereby ſhe loſt at the leaſt a pottle of Blood; I ſtayed the Blood and cured her Leg.</p>
               <p>A young Maid as ſhe vvas cutting Sticks vvith an Ax, by chance cut her Leg ſorely, ſhe having long time been afflicted vvith the Green-ſickneſs and Dropſie; I not only Cured her Leg, but alſo her other Diſtempers at the ſame time.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151469:14"/>
               <p> A Gentleman having got a bruiſe on his Leg by the laſh of a Whip, and being in a deſperate condition with it, ſo that he was in danger of his life, I in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent time did Cure.</p>
               <p>Many of the Convulſion-fits, and Rickets among Children I did Cure.</p>
               <p>One being bitten with a Mad-Dog, I in very ſhort time did Cure him.</p>
               <p>Several Women who had ſore Breaſts and ſore Nipples, I Cured.</p>
               <p>Many who had violent fits of the Stone, I eaſed them.</p>
               <p>A Man being much bruiſed with the fall of a Cart upon him, I cured.</p>
               <p>One being much bruiſed by Rogues meeting him on the way, and after they had beaten him down, kicked him on one ſide of his Head, ſo that his Ear was ſwelled you could ſee no ſhape it had, and withal fell into a Feavor: I, by Gods help did Cure.</p>
               <p>A Woman who for divers Months had a very great Flux upon her, I ſpeedily Cured.</p>
               <p>A man lying ſick of the Meazles, and being all ſtruck in, ſo that it was thought he could not poſſibly have lived, I gave him a Cordial which brought them forth again and recovered him.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151469:15"/>
               <p> A Child of a year old being taken with the ſhaking Palſie, I Cured.</p>
               <p>A Man having a Pitch-fork run into the Corner of his Eye, I Cured.</p>
               <p>A Woman having a Stick run into the corner of her Eye, I Cured.</p>
               <p>A little Boy falling from a Bridge into a little River, cut his Head ſo with a ſtone, that while I had it in Cure there came forth a ſliver of the Skull; I Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>A Man taken ſuddenly with an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex, as he walked the Street, his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours taking him into a Houſe, and as they thought he was quite dead, I being called unto him, chanced to come juſt when they had taken the Pillow from his Head, and were going to ſtrip him; but I cauſed him to be ſet upright, and his mouth to be open by force, then did I give him ſomething out of a little glaſs, and cauſed him to be rubbed and chaffed, and Air to be given him, ſo that in a little time he came to himſelf and knew every one: He lived about ten hours after, and gave God and me thanks, that he was not taken away in that condition, but gave him ſence to make his Peace with God and to order what he had left. I willed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151469:15"/> him to ſend for a Phyſician; which he did, who did approve of what I had done, but could not ſave his life.</p>
               <p>A Woman being ſtruck with a ſtaff upon the Lip, ſo that it was cut aſunder with the blow: I in ſhort time Cured.</p>
               <p>Many I did cure in that Town, which were burned with Fire, and ſome ſcalded, and none of them had a Scar.</p>
               <p>A Girle about twelve years of Age being taken with a Lethargy, and after I had brought her out of it ſhe fell into ſtrong and ſtrange Convulſion-fits, which in few weeks I did perfectly Cure.</p>
               <p>After theſe Seven years were paſt, we lived at <hi>Hackney,</hi> near <hi>London,</hi> where we had above threeſcore Boarders; and there I had many more Trials for my Skill both at home and abroad.</p>
               <p>I Cured my own Son of an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume in the Head, and of a deep Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, after the Phyſicians had given him over.</p>
               <p>I Cured a Woman of Threeſcore years old, who had lyen Bed-ridden half a year of a Timpany, and was not able to help her ſelf: This Cure I did in three days.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151469:16"/>
               <p> I Cured a Man-ſervant to a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who had a ſore Leg by a fall from an high place, and it was grown ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, that it was thought incurable.</p>
               <p>I Cured a Bricklayer who had a ſore Leg by the fall of Timber, and becauſe he was poor his Chirurgion gave it over.</p>
               <p>I Cured a Shoe-maker of a ſore Leg, who had ſpent three pounds on it before he came to me.</p>
               <p>I Cured a poor Woman of a ſore Leg, who was adviſed by a Chirurgion to have it cut off.</p>
               <p>A Cancer in the Noſe I have Cured.</p>
               <p>Cankers in the Mouth and Throat.</p>
               <p>The Green-ſickneſs in many. Dropſie, Jaundies, Scurvy, Sciatica, Griping of the Guts, Vomiting and Looſneſs.</p>
               <p>And for the Palſie, whether Dead or Shaking, I am ſure none can give better Remedies, nor know it better than I do, having bought my Experience at a dear rate; there is none who have been more afflicted with it than my ſelf, and (I humbly bleſs God for it) there is no Perſon more freer from it than my ſelf, nor from any other Diſeaſe, and that is very much, I being now in my Two and fiftieth year.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151469:16"/>
               <p> Much more I could ſay, but I think I need not; for they who do believe any thing I write, will, I hope, have confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to make uſe of theſe Receipts I ſhall give them without any fear. It is altogether as neceſſary that you ſhould know how to keep your Bodies in health, to preſerve your Eye-ſight and your Limbs, as it is to Feed or Cloath your ſelf. Therefore the more fully to accompliſh you, let me perſwade you not to ſlight, but to value what I ſhall teach, and give God the glory; who out of ſo mean things as I ſhall name, he ſhould, of his goodneſs to us, create in them ſo great a vertue. I do not attribute any thing but to his alone power, and give him praiſe when he pleaſeth to make me an Inſtrument of doing good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151469:17"/>
               <head>For any Ague whatever.</head>
               <p>TAke of the dried leaves of Lawrel which is eſteemed in Gardens: Take of the fine powder thereof as much as will lie upon a ſixpence by heap, mix it vvith any liquid thing, and take it one hour or two before the fit comes; do this three times and go to bed, and keep warm.</p>
               <p>The beſt thing to give it in is Treacle-water, Cardus-water, or Dragon-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the falling Sickneſs.</head>
               <p>Take a live Mole, and cut the throat of it into a Glaſs of Whitewine, and preſently give it to the party to drink at the New and Full of the Moon <hi>(viz.)</hi> the day before the New, the day of the Nevv, and the day after, and ſo at the Full.</p>
               <p>This vvill Cure abſolutely, if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be not above forty years of Age.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:151469:17"/>
               <head>For an extream Rheum falling from the Head.</head>
               <p>Take ſome <hi>Lucatelia</hi> Balſom, and ſpread it thin upon the ſmooth ſides of red Sage leaves, take five or ſix of theſe leaves with the other ſide downward upon a few embers of Wood Coals, and take the ſmoak through a paper tunnel into your mouth; thus do every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing till you find a Cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Worms, a miraculous Cure.</head>
               <p>Let the party drink their own Water with a little Methridate mingled therein, for three days together in the morning faſting, and walk after it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A moſt excellent Oyntment for all manner of ſwellings and ſores, and for the Kings Evil, it will diſſolve it if it be to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, it will both break and heal; it is good alſo for ſore Eyes if anointed therewith.</head>
               <p>Take one pint of the juyce of <hi>Cellon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine,</hi> and boil it in one pound and half of new Butter never ſalted, till you may by your judgment think it to be enough,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151469:18"/> ſo keep it in a Gally-pot for your uſe, and when you apply it let it be warm, and bath the place well, if it be not broken, but if it be broken, then dip fine linnen Cloths in it and lay on twice in the day, anoint ſore Eyes gently with a Feather, every night till they are well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A moſt excellent Balſom for Wounds.</head>
               <p>Take a pint of the pureſt ſallad Oyl, and put to it four ounces of common Brimſtone beaten fine, and ſet it in the Sun for three weeks or more before you uſe it.</p>
               <p>If the Wound be inflamed, ſpread ſome conſerve of Red-roſes upon a linnen Cloth, and lay on over night, the next Morning bath it well with Brandy, and then lay on this Balſom with a Feather warm, uſe the Conſerve of Roſes till you find the inflammation to be quite gone, and if you perceive proud fleſh to grow in the Wound, then lay in a little burnt Allom after you have waſhed it, before you lay on the Balſom.</p>
               <p>Conſerve of Red-roſes is alſo very good to lay upon inflamed Eyes, moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned firſt with a few drops of Plantain Water,</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:151469:18"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:151469:19"/>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151469:19"/>
               <head>For Madneſs, and for fumes in the Head.</head>
               <p>Rub the ſoles of the Feet with the Spirit of Brandy every night, and apply the Herb Henbane, bruiſed with a little Nutmeg and Whitewine Vinegar to the Temples; it will eaſe pain in the Head, and cauſe the Party to ſleep.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For pain in the Bones.</head>
               <p>Anoint the place grieved with Dogs greaſe every night by the fire, and wear ſocks cut out of a Bears skin in their Shoes every day, and their pain will be gone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Leproſie, or any other venemous Humour.</head>
               <p>Swallow every twelve hours a bullet of Gold, and ſtill as you void one waſh it in Treacle-vvater, and at the due hour ſwallow it again; continue doing this a long time and it vvill Cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To kill Rats.</head>
               <p>Fry a Spung in Butter and hang it by a ſtring, and the Rats vvill forſake the Room.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151469:20"/>
               <head>To Cure a Horſe of a Cold, though he hath had it never ſo long a time.</head>
               <p>Take two new laid Eggs, put them into an Earthen-pot, and then put in as much Whitewine Vinegar as will cover them, then cover them cloſe and put them into a Horſe-dunghill and cover it over with the dung, ſo let it ſtand twelve hours, then pour it down the Horſes throat ſhells and all, and gallop him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, and Cloath him very warm; be ſure you give it him three or four times, but there muſt be a day between every time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a Cow that Stales bloud.</head>
               <p>Take a good handful of the Herb called Peruwinckle and bruiſe it, and boyl it in a quart of Ale till it comes to a pint, then ſtrain it and give it her to drink; do ſo three times. Peruwinckle hath alſo an excellent vertue to ſtench bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Noſe in Chriſtians, if it be made into a garland and hung about the Neck.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:151469:20"/>
               <head>An excellent Medicine for the Cold Gout.</head>
               <p>Take Stone-pitch three drams, pound it to duſt, and ſet it over the fire; Venice Turpentine ſo much as being mingled with the Pitch, will make it ſpread when the Pitch is cold; the beſt Turmerick, 5 or 6 Races beaten to powder, Letharge of Gold half an ounce; mix all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when you have warmed the Pitch, and work them together that all may become one ſubſtance, and uſe it for your Plaiſter, following the Gout as it ſhall remove.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Hot Gout, A moſt admirable Medicine.</head>
               <p>Take the Bones of a Horſes Legs, break them, and take the Marrow out of them and waſh it clean, it muſt be the whiteſt Marrow, waſh the Bones alſo, and put both the Marrow and them into a Kettle with Running-water, and ſet them a boyling, ſcim off the firſt riſing for that will be froth, then ſcim of all the reſt that ariſeth and ſave it, as you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151469:21"/> do the Neats-foot Oyl; then take of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop, Time, Camomile, Roſemary, and ſix leaves of red Sage (of all) the quantity of a handful, and when you have got as much Oil as you can, then boil the Herbs in it for a quarter of an hour, then ſtrain it and keep it in a Gally-pot or Glaſs; the quantity of a ſmall Nut will go a great way; you muſt ſtrip the Roſemary and Time upwards, and be ſure you put in none of the ſtalks; put in as much Sothernwood-tops and of Lavender Cotton, as you did of each of the other Herbs, and boil them with the other, keep it well from the Air.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent Gliſter to Cool and Bind.</head>
               <p>Take a quart of new Milk, and a handful of Knot-graſs, as much of Bramble, as much of ſmall Plantain; boil theſe together in the Milk, then ſtrain it, and put in ſix penny weight of Bolear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack, and adminiſter it blood-warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:151469:21"/>
               <head>For the running-Gout, or any hot Tumor.</head>
               <p>Take Mallows, Violet leaves, Marſh-Mallows, Melilot, of each two handfuls, Linſeeds beaten two ounces, Crumbs of Bread as much; boil theſe in Milk and make a Poultis therewith; then put into it a little Oil of Roſes, and apply it to the grieved place very warm twice a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To Cure a Deafneſs which is cauſed by the ſtoppage of the Ears by wax.</head>
               <p>If it hath been long, then drop into the Ear a little of Bitter-Almonds warmed, for a week together every Night; when the Party is in Bed then take a little warmed Sack, with as much of the beſt white Anniſeed-water, and ſeringe the Ears with it once a day for three days together, and keep them ſtopped with black Wool. If they have been deaf but a little while, then the Wine with the Anniſeed-water will be ſufficient, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Oil of Almonds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:151469:22"/>
               <head>For the falling down of the Mother.</head>
               <p>Take Smiths Water and Oaken leaves, or the Bark of Oak, and boil them well in a Pewter diſh cloſe covered, then ſtrain it through a Cloth; wet Cloaths therein and apply them hot two or three times in a Night when you go to Bed: Thus do for a week together, and keep your ſelf warm in the day time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A moſt excellent Plaiſter for the Gout, wherewith a Gentleman as I knew was Cured after all the Chirurgions had given him over.</head>
               <p>Take half a pound of un-wrought Wax, half a pound of Roſin, one ounce of Olibenum, four ounces of Letharge of Gold, three quarters of a pound of White-lead finely beaten and ſearced; then take a pint of Neats-foot Oyl, ſet it on the fire with the Wax and Roſin, and when it is melted put thereto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther powders, and ſtir it faſt with a ſtick till you find it be enough: ſo make it up in Rouls, and keep it for your uſe, and when you feel any pain apply it upon linnen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151469:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>For the biting of a Mad-dog, taught by Doctor</hi> Mathias.</head>
               <p>Take of Rue, of Garlick, of ſcraped Pewter, of each two ounces, of Venice-Treacle one ounce, of Muſcadine one quart; put all theſe into it, ſtop it cloſe and boil it in a Kettle of water for the ſpace of two hours, then pour off the cleareſt, and apply ſome of the dregs to the place bitten, and give the Patient two ſpoonfuls to drink of the Liquor, Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening for nine days together. This never failed Man nor Beaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make the Oil of Charity.</head>
               <p>Take Roſemary, Sage, Lavender, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, the leſſer Valerian, of each one handful; cut them ſmall and put them into Oyl-Olive, let it be very thick with the Herbs, let it infuſe ſeven daies in the Sun; then take the Glaſs wherein they are and wind about the bottom a little Hay, and ſet it into a Kettle of ſeething Water, and let it ſtand two hours; then ſtrain it out and put in Herbs; and do as before, ſo do three times; then put in Valerian alone and do as before, then
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151469:23"/> ſtrain it and let the Oyl ſettle: keep the cleareſt for Chriſtians, and the grounds and Herbs for Beaſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Vertues.</head>
               <p>It healeth green-Wounds and Bruiſes (if inwardly:) Take a ſpoonfull of the cleareſt Oil in a little warm Poſſet-drink, and go to Bed and ſweat after it. It cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Tooth-ach if it comes of a cold Rheum, dipping Clothes in it and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay to the Cheek. It is good for all Aches that come of Cold. It is good for Deafneſs, if it be dropped into the Ear warm; if firſt the head be carefully opened with the ſtream of red-Sage and Milk boiled together. It will alſo Cure or knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a broken Rib.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To Cure a Timpany. Proved by me.</head>
               <p>Take ſhell-Snails, crack their ſhells and take them off, then put the Snails into a Cullender for a little while to drain, then beat them in a Wooden-Boul or Mortar till you find they are well beaten; then warm it a little in a ſtone-Pan and ſpread it upon Sheeps-leather, and lay it all over the Belly when the Party goes to Bed, and bind it on: the next Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning take it off, and lay in the ſtead thereof a warm Cloth. Thus do three Nights together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151469:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To make the Black-water, to Cure a Thiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Woolf;</hi> Noli me tangere; <hi>or any Tetter or Scald; or any other Sores.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the fatteſt Wool about the Cod of a Sheep, dry it in an Oven after Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold-Bread is drawn; then beat it into fine powder; put to it a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of white Roſe-water, with a little Mercury ſublimate, and ſo apply it to the grieved places, by wetting linnen Rags and lay it on warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A moſt excellent Diet-drink for any Diſeaſe, cauſed by ſharp or foul Humors.</head>
               <p>Take Saſa-perilla 4 ounces, Saſafras-wood 4 ounces, and China-root 1 ounce, 4 handfuls of Egrimony, 4 handfuls of Colts-foot, 4 handfuls of Scabions, 2 pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worth of Marſh-Mallow-root, one handful of Betony, 1 handful of Ladies-mantle, 1 handful of Sanicle, and 1 root of Columbine; ſhread the Roots above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and put them together with the Herbs into three gallons of Running-water; boil it to two Gallons, then ſtrain it, and put to the water one gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon more of Water, and boil it until it be half conſumed; then ſtrain this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151469:24"/> drink, and put thereto one pottle of Whitewine, and one pint and half of Hony, boil it a little again and ſcum it very clean, then take it from the fire, and put in two ounces of Sena, and three quarters of an ounce of Rubarb; drink a draught thereof Morning and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening: It is good for Dropſie and Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a Film in the Eye.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hony, and the Marrow of a Gooſe wing, of each a like quantity, warm them together, and lay them on the Eyelid with a Feather, and let it go into the Eye, dreſs it twice a day till it be well. It will cure thoſe films which do come of the ſmall Pox.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To Cure ſore Nipples, or for abruiſe which comes by a fall.</head>
               <p>Take Perſley and ſhred it, and boyl it in Cream till you ſee an oil on the top of it; then take that oil and boil with a little Loaf Sugar, and ſo apply it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Stone and Choler.</head>
               <p>Half an ounce of Caſſia in the Cane, taken from the point of a knife, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151469:24"/> after it half an ounce of Manna, diſſolved in Poſſet-drink, and two hours after that drink Lemmon Poſſet-drink: This you muſt do three days together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make Thiſtolow Water.</head>
               <p>Take of Bolearmoniack four ounces, Camphire four ounces, white Coperus one ounce; ſlice the Camphire thin and beat the Coperus fine; then boil them two together in an Earthen-Pan never uſed, they will melt of themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thing to them; when they are melted, ſtir them together with a little ſtick till they are hard, then beat them in a Mortar to a powder, and then beat your Bolearmoniack and mix with them very well, and keep it tied up in a blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (it will keep ſeven years:) when you uſe of it, take a quart of Spring-water and make it boiling hot, then put in one good ſpoonful of the powder and ſtir it about, and when it is cold put it into a Glaſs, and cover it: When you dreſs any Wound or Thiſtolow with it, you muſt warm it very hot, and bath the place well with it, then double ſome ſoft Rags and wet them in it, having
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151469:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:151469:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:151469:26"/> before a little Hony in the heating of it; ſo lay on your wetted Rags, and bind them on: thus do twice a day till it be well. This heals very faſt, if the Wound be fit to be healed; but if there be any inflammation in it, it is not for it.</p>
               <p>If you uſe it for the Eyes, you muſt warm it, and drop it in. I did Cure a Gentlewoman of a Thiſtolow in the Eye with it, which ſhe had by the Small-Pox: And ſeveral ſore Legs I have Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with it.</p>
               <p>It is very good for the Itch (and for Gald-Horſe backs) only you muſt dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your quantity of powder, and always put in Hony when you heat it; for that doth cleanſe and help to heal.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Rheum in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Dragons-blood, Bole-armoniack, and Maſtick beaten and ſearſt, of each a like quantity; mix them with the white of an Egg well beaten: then ſpread it on a piece of Leather, and lay it on the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, from one Temple to another, and let it lie till you be Cured; which, with Gods bleſſing, will be in three days.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:151469:26"/>
               <head>To ſtench Bleeding at the Noſe, or in Wounds.</head>
               <p>Take of Frankinſence one dram, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes half a dram, beat them into fine powder; then beat the white of an Egg and mix with it, let it be of the thickneſs of Hony; dip the wool of a Hare in it, and apply it to the Wound, and bind it on: if to the Noſe, ſpread it upon a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen Cloth, and lay it to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Kibed Heels.</head>
               <p>Take the Wool of a Cony, and the white of an Egg, beaten together, and ſpread it upon a linnen Cloth and lay it on: but if they are broken, then take a live-Mouſe and flea it, and lay the skin on while it is warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Rickets in Children.</head>
               <p>Take of the inner Bark of Ivy, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Bark of Aſh, Harts-tongue leaves, branches of Tamerisk, boil them in ſour Gallons of middle-Wort, and put in ſo many of Hops as you think will keep it: when it is cold enough, work it up with Yeaſt as you do
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151469:27"/> other drink, have one Veſſel under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and let the Child drink no other drink for a quarter of a year. I have cured many with this drink, and a Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Paracelſus upon Sheeps leather to the ſmall of the back.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent Remedy for the Stone.</head>
               <p>Take White-wine and quench a black Flint in it five ſeveral times, then ſweeten it with Sirrup of Marſh-Mallows, and take it Morning and Evening for three days.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent Cordial Electuary.</head>
               <p>Take of Conſerve of Sage-flowers, Roſemary-flowers, Marigold-flowers, and of red-Roſes, of each one ounce, mix them together with one ounce of Sirrup of Clove-gilly flowers, and ſix ſheets of leaf-Gold; keep it in a Gally-pot, and take every night when you go to bed as much as a little Walnut. It is very good for any weak Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Bloudy-Flux, or other Looſneſs.</head>
               <p>Take two or three Races of Ginger and ſlice them thin, and lay ſome of them
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151469:27"/> ever a Chaffing-diſh of Coals; then ſit over the heat and ſmoak of it, and take heed you catch no Cold: Do this Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening for three or four days.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Worms in Children.</head>
               <p>Take of the tops of unſet-Leeks, with the lower part alſo of them, one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as much of the tops of Wormwood; chop them ſmall; then ſet them on the fire with a little freſh Butter and a little Whitewine Vinegar, and boil them till the Herbs be ſoft, and that it be reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thick; then put it between two linnen Clothes ſewed like a Bag, and lay it warm all over the belly of the Child at Night, and bind it on with a Cloth. The next Morning take it off and put a warm Cloth inſtead thereof.</p>
               <p>Thus do three or four Nights toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and it will cauſe them to void the Worms. It doth alſo draw Wind and infection out of the Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a black Salve very good for Corns, or for any Sore old or new.</head>
               <p>Take a pint of ſallad Oyl, and half a pound of Red-lead, and put them into a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151469:28"/> skillet that will hold three pints, or near, for fear of boyling over; ſtir it all the while, and let it boil ſoftly till you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to look black, and that it leave boiling and doth ſmoak; then take it from the fire, and let it ſtand till it be quite cold, then warm the bottom of the Skillet and turn it out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent Water for a Canker in the Mouth, or for any Sore.</head>
               <p>Take of Roſemary, Sage, Plantain and Scurvy-graſs, of each one handful, one little branch of Herb of Grace, and a little Sweet-bryer; boil theſe in a quart of Water and a quart of White-wine, and put therein a bright ſhining Sea-coal as big as an Egg, one that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver burned; let them boil ſoftly over a ſlow-fire, cloſe covered, till half be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; then ſtrain it out and put in ſome Roach-allom; make it ſharp with it; then make it very ſweet with Hony, and ſet over the fire again till it be boyling hot; then when it is almoſt cold put it into a Glaſs-bottle, and keep it for uſe. When you uſe it, waſh your Mouth with it very hot, three or four times in a day; and then take a little warm Hony in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151469:28"/> your Mouth to eaſe the ſmart: Bath-Wounds with it very hot and well, then dip linnen Clothes in warm Hony and lay on. Dreſs it twice a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very ſine Poultis to lay on any Sore, to take the inflammation out of it; or to lay to a ſore Breaſt to break, or to diſſolve it if it will not break: It will alſo heal it if broken.</head>
               <p>Take a quart of Milk, and boil it with two ſlight handfuls of Oatmeal, and one good handful of white-Lilly leaves (I mean the green leaves of the white Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies cut ſmall) when it is boiled enough, put in as much of the beſt ſallad Oil as will make it very ſoft and moiſt; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the bigneſs of your Sore ſpread ſome of it upon a linnen Cloth, and lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it as hot as you can ſuffer it Morning and Evening: when you dreſs it waſh it with a little Brandy and Butter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a tickling Rheum and Cough.</head>
               <p>Take of Conſerve of Fox-lungs two ounces, Sirrup of Colts-foot, Sirrup of Maiden-hair, Sirrup of Hore-hound, Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup of Hyſop, Sirrup of Violets, of each one ounce; mix them well together, and take them often in the day or night upon a Liquoriſh-ſtick.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:151469:29"/>
               <head>An excellent Balſom for inward Bruiſes, for outward Wounds, and for the Stone.</head>
               <p>Take of Oyl-Olive, Oyl of Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and of the beſt Whitewine, of each one quart, put into them three good handfuls of the tops of St. <hi>Johns</hi> Wort, with the flowers and ſeeds; let them ſtand in a Glaſs in the Sun ten daies; then put them into a long Gally-pot, and ſet that pot into a Kettle of water, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten it with Hay; let the water ſeeth for two hours, then take it out and ſet it by: alwaies keep it covered.</p>
               <p>If you take it for the Stone, take a ſpoonful of it at a time in a Glaſs of Whitewine, in the Morning faſting, for three days together at the New and Full of the Moon; but if you ſhould be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly taken, then take it when your ſelf is in pain.</p>
               <p>For Sores, warm it a little, and after you have vvell vvaſhed the Wound with Brandy, lay on the Balſom with a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and dip Lint in it and lay into it, and a piece of Hogs-bladder over that, that the linnen you bind it up with may not ſoak it up, dreſs your wounds Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:151469:29"/>
               <p> If you take it for an inward Bruiſe, take two ſpoonfuls of it in a Glaſs of Whitewine, and go to bed and ſweat, do ſo three nights together; be ſure to jum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the pot well together when you take any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or elſe the Oils vvill be at the top, and the Wine at the bottom; the Herbs and Flowers applyed ſtench bleeding in Wounds, or at the Noſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A moſt admirable Drink for a Cough: it alſo expelleth any congealed Blood, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtume, or other filthy Humour. It healeth all inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers, and cooleth inflamed Lungs, and alſo healeth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in them.</head>
               <p>Take two pounds of quick-Lime, and put it into ten quarts of Spring-water in an Earthen-pot; let it ſtand twenty four hours; then you will ſee as it were a thin ice on the top of it, which you muſt take off very clean with a ſcimmer, then pour off all that is clear into another pot, and put into it theſe things following:</p>
               <p>Of blew Figgs ſlit in two half a pound, of Raiſons of the Sun ſtoned half a pound, of Liquoriſh ſcraped and ſliced thin four ounces, of China Root ſliced
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151469:30"/> thin two ounces, of Anniſeeds bruiſed one ounce, of the ſhavings of Ivory four ounces, of Maiden-hair one handful, of Burrage, of Pimpernel, of Balm, of Penny-Royal, of Colts-foot, Scabions, Horehound, of St. <hi>Johns</hi> Wort, of each one handful, and half a handful of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigold flowers; then put in four ounces of Earth-worms, ſlit and cleanſed from their filth with Whitewine.</p>
               <p>Let all theſe ſteep in that water 24 hours; then take it and ſtrain it gently and keep it in Glaſs-bottles; drink there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Morning and Evening a good draught (or if you pleaſe) oftener, and you will find a great benefit.</p>
               <p>Take two pounds more of quick-Lime, and put it into the ſame quantity of Spring-water, and do as you did before; only you may uſe the ſame Ingredients as you made the other, without any new.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151469:30"/>
               <head>For a Pin and Web in the Eye.</head>
               <p>Take of red-Roſewater one quarter of a pint, put into it two pennyworth of Maſtick finely powdered, and one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce of white Sugar-Candy; then have in readineſs of burnt-Allom, and white Sugar-Candy, of each a like quantity beaten fine and ſearſed, and mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed well together: When you dreſs the Eye, firſt waſh it well with the Water, and then blow in ſome of the powder with a quill, and hold your hand over it till the ſmart be gone; the next Morning let ſome Breaſt-milk be milked into it, and do nothing elſe in the Morning; and every Evening uſe the other: ſo do till your Eye be well.</p>
               <p>Do not put any Cloth, or Silk before your Eye, for that poyſons it, by cauſing the venemous humor to return.</p>
               <p>This Water is very good for other Sore-Eyes, if they be well waſhed with it Morning and Evening, and if the Rheum be very much in the Eyes; then lay a plaiſter of Burgundy-Pitch to the Nape of the Neck, and let it lie as long as it will ſtick.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:151469:31"/>
               <head>For the Tooth-ach.</head>
               <p>Anoint that ſide of the face on which the Tooth-ach is, from the Temple down to the lower part of the Ear (upon all thoſe Veins which carry the Rheum to the Teeth) with a few drops of Oil of Amber; work it well with your hand and gently, then ſpread a black Ribbon two penny broad with Maſtick, and lay it upon the place which you did anoint, and keep it on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a Thruſh in a Childs mouth.</head>
               <p>Waſh it Morning and Evening with a little Verjuyce and Hony, warmed a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and then blow in ſome white Sugar-Candy beaten fine with a quill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Itch.</head>
               <p>Take ſome common Brimſtone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beaten fine, and mix a little beaten Ginger with it; then tie it up in a Tiffany or Lawn, and let it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>lie in ſtrong Whitewine Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar with ſome Roach-Allom; when it hath lien all night you may begin to uſe it, but the longer it lies the better it will be; when you uſe it, take up the Cloth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151469:31"/> wherein the Brimſtone is tied, and rub all your Joynts with it very well every night when you go to bed; then take a little Methridate before you go to bed; ſo do till you are Cured. It is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous thing to cure the Itch, and not to drive it out, for that ſtrikes it in, and many times it falls upon the Lungs; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it cauſes Convulſion-fits, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexies or Lethargies if not driven out.</p>
               <p>It is alſo very neceſſary when you have quite killed and cured it, to purge the Party very well, to prevent further miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a Bruiſe where no skin is broken.</head>
               <p>There is no better thing than to bath it well with Oil of Spike, morning and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a Sinew-ſtrain.</head>
               <p>Take ſtrong Beer or Ale and boil it till it be very thin, then ſpread it upon Leather, and lay it on as hot as you can ſuffer it, and let it ſtay on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:151469:32"/>
               <head>For a Conſumption, or other weakneſs.</head>
               <p>Take a Gallon of ſtrong Ale-wort, and put therein two ounces of Liquoriſh ſcraped clean and ſliced thin, and one ounce of Anniſeeds bruiſed; boil them together till it be very thick; then ſtrain it while it is hot, and keep it in a Gally-pot, and take thereof every Morning and Evening: It is a very good Remedy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a Burn.</head>
               <p>Take the juyce of a great Onion, and put to it three ſpoonfuls of Fair-water, and as much pure ſallad Oil, and beat it together very well with two or three Feathers tied together; beat it till it be thick and white, and lay it on with a Feather; then lay on very thin Raggs dipped therein; dreſs it three times in a day, for you muſt not let it be dry; and when you do dreſs it, anoint the Cloths with ſome of it before you take them off, that they may come eaſily: the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of them off when they are hard and dry is that which makes a Scar.</p>
               <p>When you perceive the fire to be quite out, then leave out the juyce of Onion
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151469:32"/> and uſe only the Oil and Water, and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure you anoint it eight or ten days after it is quite well.</p>
               <p>I have Cured many Burnings, and ſome with Gunpowder, without a Scar, with this Medicine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Shingles.</head>
               <p>Take a Cat, and cut off her Ears, or her Tail, and mix the Blood thereof with a little new-Milk, and anoint the grieved place with it Morning and Evening for three days; and every night vvhen the Party goes to Bed give her or him two ſpoonfuls of Treacle-water, to drive out the venom.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To take away the pain in the Huckle-bone, or for any Old ach.</head>
               <p>Take of Burgundy-Pitch, Oxicroſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, and Paracelſus, of each a like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, melt them together in an Earthen-Porringer, and ſpread them upon Sheeps-leather; then anoint the grieved place vvith Oil of Amber, and lay on your Plaiſter.</p>
               <p>This is very good alſo for any Sprain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:151469:33"/>
               <head>For one who is ſuddenly taken with a Numbneſs in any Limb.</head>
               <p>Take Brandy and Muſtard, and warm them well together, and bath the place very well with it twice a day for a week together, and it will work a wonderful effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To take away any extream pain in the Head in any Sickneſs.</head>
               <p>At your going to reſt, let a linnen Cloth be dipped in Aquavite, and laid all over the Forehead from one Temple to another; then dip little linnen Rags in Cinnamon-water and put up the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, let them not be too ſhort for fear the breath draw them into the Head.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For an Impoſtume in the Ear.</head>
               <p>Take a great Onion and roaſt it in a paper wetted (in wood-Embers) when it is enough, put to it two pennyworth of Saffron, and a little ſpoonful of ſallad Oil, and work them well together with the back of a Spoon; then apply it on a linnen Cloth to the hole of the Ear as hot as the Party can ſuffer it, at the time
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151469:33"/> of going to reſt, and the next day when you take it off, put a warm Cloth inſtead thereof; thus do three Nights together, and when you find that it is broken and well drawn out: Seringe the Ear with a little warm Sack and Betony-water for three days together, twice a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Deafneſs in Young or Old.</head>
               <p>Take Brine which comes from Beef at the firſt ſalting, and boil it very well, and ſcum it well, and keep it in a Glaſs for your uſe:</p>
               <p>Then take the Kidney-Suet of a Loin of Mutton, and ſhave it very thin, and when the Party goes to Bed, fill the hole of the Ear that is grieved with ſome of the Suet, and ſtop it with Black-wool, and let him lie on the other ſide that it fall not out, and as he ſleeps it will melt into the Ear; thus do for a Week every Night: when that is done, then take three or four drops of the Brine in a Spoon and warm it a little, and drop into the Ear every night for a Week.</p>
               <p>This hath done very much good to one of Fourſcore years Old.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:151469:34"/>
               <head>For the Emorroids or Piles.</head>
               <p>Take of Unguentum Album, vvhich you have at the Apothecaries commonly; melt it over the fire vvith a little ſallad Oil, and put in a little of the beſt Bole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armoniack; apply it upon a linnen Cloth every Night vvhen you go to bed till you are vvell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For to Cure Heart-burning.</head>
               <p>Take prepared Crabs-Eyes, and mix leaf-Gold therein, and keep them in a Box; and when you find your Heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to burn, lick two or three times of the powder, and it vvill Cure you for that time, and be a means to keep it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for the future. Alſo a draught of Milk never at all boiled doth help it; but the other Medicine is much better.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the paſſion of the Heart.</head>
               <p>Take as much Confection of Alker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes as a Pea, in a drop or two of Sirrup of Clove-Gilly-flowers, and it will caſe you in ſuch an inſtant, as you cannot but admire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is beyond all things that ever I uſed, and not of much coſt. Take heed that it be good Alkermes, for there is much of deceit uſed in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:151469:34"/>
               <head>For the Cramp in the Legs.</head>
               <p>Take a lock of black-Thred, about half an ounce, and dip it in ſuch Oil as they greaze Wool withal; then draw it through your hands very well that the Oil may not drop from it; then vvind it about your Thighs, and tie it and keep it on day and night. Eel-skins are alſo good to tie about the Thighs; but firſt they muſt be made gentle and eaſie.</p>
               <p>And that which is as good as either of theſe, is to anoint the grieved parts vvith Oil of Spike a vveek together. The ſame perfectly Cures a Crick in the neck, in two or three times uſing. I like the latter beſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To Cure a Scabbed-Head, and to kill the Lice.</head>
               <p>Take the yolks of ſix hard Eggs, and bruiſe them well with a ſpoon; then put one pound of new-Butter to them that vvas never ſalted; boil them together till you find it to be enough, which will be in an hours ſpace, upon a ſlow fire; let it look blackiſh when you take it off the fire; then ſtrain it and keep it for your
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151469:35"/> uſe; anoint the Head very well with it twice a day, and it will ſoon deſtroy both Scabs and Lice in a ſhort time, to much admiration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Chilblanes on the Hands.</head>
               <p>So ſoon as you find your Fingers begin to itch, ſpread ſome Burgundy Pitch upon Leather, and lay round about your Arms; let the Plaiſters be four-fingers broad, and lay them four-fingers above your hand.</p>
               <p>They will ſoon abate the itching, and draw forth the humor where they lie, not ſuffering it any more to fall into your hands. Waſh your hands every day with right Venice Soap, and that will help you in the Cure. This is a very certain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to my knowledge. It alſo Cureth ſore hands that are crackt and chopt with a ſharp humour, if you lay the Plaiſters round about the upper-part of your Arm above the Elbow, and waſh with the ſame Soap</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:151469:35"/>
               <head>To kill the Scurvy before you purge.</head>
               <p>Take of Scurvy-graſs, of Worm-wood and Sage, of each half a handful, with a little Rue; put them into a pint of Whitewine, and let them boil ſoftly till half be conſum'd, cloſe covered; then ſtrain it, and put in as much Saffron as will well colour it.</p>
               <p>Divide this into three parts, and take every Morning one; then take this Purge following:</p>
               <p>Take five Gallons of Ale, put into it a quarter of a peck of Garden-Scurvy-graſs bruiſed, two great handfuls of Sage, two ounces of Horſe-Radiſh-root ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and ſliced very thin, Red-Dock-root ſliced very thin two ounces, Anniſeeds bruiſed one ounce and an half, Liquoriſh ſcraped and ſliced thin four ounces, Sena two ounces, Figs ſliced thin half a pound. When your Ale hath done working, put in all theſe things and ſtop it up; when it hath been four days, then drink every Morning a pint, and again at four in the After-noon, till you have drunk all the Ale. With this I have Cured many who were very bad.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:151469:36"/>
               <head>For a Squinacy, or other ſore Throat.</head>
               <p>Take the whiteſt dung of a Dog, which he hath dunged abroad in <hi>May,</hi> let it dry in the Sun very well, and when you have occaſion to uſe it, beat it fine and ſearce it, and give the Party thereof a ſlight ſpoonful in a Glaſs of White-wine; and mix ſome with Hony, and ſpread it and lay to the Throat: let the Plaiſter lie on, and take the other three Nights and it will Cure you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a Red-face.</head>
               <p>Every Night waſh your Face with this following: Take Fumitory-water half a pint, a little lump of Allom, and a little white Sugar-Candy; with the juyce of one Lemmon, and as much common Brimſtone beaten fine as will lye upon a half Crown heaped. Do not wipe your Face when you have waſhed it, but let it dry in.</p>
               <p>Every Morning drink a Glaſs of old <hi>Malago-Sack,</hi> and eat a little Toaſt dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped therein.</p>
               <p>It will be very good for you to Purge every Spring, if you find much heat in it, which you may know by a dry hot hand, and inward heat.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:151469:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:151469:37"/>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:151469:37"/>
               <p> be ſure to ſhift them often, till the Coar be drawn out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a Plague-Sore.</head>
               <p>Take Figgs half a pound, and of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as much; beat them together ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly well; then ſpread ſome of it upon a Burdock-leaf, if you can have one, or elſe upon a linnen Cloth: dreſs it twice a day; this will both break and heal it. Uſe it till it be quite well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent Medicine preſcribed by a Worthy Phyſician, againſt the Plague and Peſtilence.</head>
               <p>Take of ſtrong White-wine Vinegar half a pint, of Spring-water one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Pint; mix them together, and put thereto one ounce of Venice-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: Take of this every Morning two ſpoonfuls, and anoint your Noſtrils with a little Methridate; for that will not ſuffer any Infection to paſs that way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:151469:38"/>
               <head>To kill Worms which breed about the Noſe.</head>
               <p>Waſh it often with Vinegar, Allom, and Brimſtone, till you find they are killed: and then uſe Pomatum every Night to ſmooth the skin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Childrens Scabbed-faces.</head>
               <p>Take Mallow-leaves, and the leaves of Red-Dock, of each a like quantity; ſhred them ſmall, and put as much ſallad Oil to them as will juſt ſtand even with them; then boil them on a ſoft fire till you find the Herbs begin to be criſpy; then preſently take it off, and ſtrain it out and keep it: Anoint the Face with it twice in a day, and every time before you dreſs it, waſh off that you laid on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with Butter and Beer. This is very good to Heal and Cleanſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Cheſt-Worms.</head>
               <p>Take a quarter of a pint of New-Milk, and when it boils put in a piece of Allom, and ſtir it about till you ſee that the Milk be well turned, then take out the Allom, and take off the Curd very
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151469:38"/> clean, and give the Party the Cleer drink, to drink in the Morning faſting: do ſo three Mornings together, and it will kill all the Worms; but then it will be neceſſary for to purge them with theſe things following:</p>
               <p>Take a pound of Pruons, and ſtew them leiſurely in fair Water; and take half an ounce of Sena and tie it up in a piece of Tiffany, with half an ounce of Liquoriſh ſcraped and ſliced thin, and a quarter of an ounce of Anniſeeds bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; let theſe ſtew in the Pipkin with the Pruons till they are enough; then every Morning faſting give four or five, or more, of the Pruons, according to the Age of the Party; and alſo two or three ſpoonfuls of the Liquor: do ſo ſo long as you ſee fitting. I have given this with very good ſucceſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A fine Julip for one in an Ague or Feaver.</head>
               <p>Take four ounces of French-Barley and waſh it well, then boil it in three quarts of Water till half be conſumed; then ſtrain the Barley from it, and put into the Water the juyce of two Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151469:39"/> and as much white Sugar-Candy as will well ſweeten it; then put in two ounces of Sirrup of Violets, and nine ſheets of Leaf-Gold cut very ſmall, give the ſick Party of this three or four times in a day, four or five ſpoonfuls at once; it is both cordial, and very pleaſant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I Think I have ſaid enough concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe things which I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy written in this little Book: I will now give you ſome Directions for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſorts of Work, which may pleaſure you in your Chambers and Cloſets.</p>
               <p>And if any of you ſhall deſire to be further informed than I can poſſibly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect in Writing; or to confirm themſelves in what they have already made Trial of, if you pleaſe to give your ſelves the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as to come to me, I ſhall give you the beſt aſſiſtance I can in any of thoſe things which I profeſs to teach, and for a competent gratuity.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151469:39"/>
               <p> I have ſet down every thing as plain as I can; and I know there are many who have done things very well by my Books only: but you may imagine that if you did learn a little by ſight of my doing, you would do much better; For if my Pen can teach you well, how much better would my Tongue and Hands do? The one to make anſwer to any Objection or Queſtion; the other to order or to ſhape any thing. So that in my opinion you would not loſe by having ſome perſonal Acquaintance with me; neither would I willingly loſe my time and labour in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming you: Therefore I beſeech you let it be thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be pleaſed to afford me ſome of your Mony; And I will repay you with my pains and Skill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That I judge to be fair on both ſides.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:151469:40"/>
               <head>Imprimis: <hi>To make Tranſparent Work.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BOil all in Earth, and let your Pipkin be three quarts full of Iſinglaſs, ſuch as you have at the Apothecaries, broken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto ſmall pieces, and a ſmall quantity of Gum-Dragon amongſt it; then fill it up with fair Water, and boil it till you find it be enough, which you may well know by dipping your Wyer therein; which muſt be ſhaped according to the Leaves or Flowers you intend it for. Strain it while it is hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now for the COLOURS.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Firſt, <hi>For Red.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Take the ſhavings of Brazil-wood, and fill your Pipkin half full with them; then fill it up with Water, and put in a little Roch-Allom; ſet it over the fire, and when it boils ſtrain it out. This and Oil-Tartar makes a Purple: Do not mix it too hot for that will ſpoil it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:151469:40"/>
                  <head>For Sea-Green.</head>
                  <p>Take one ounce of Verdigreace, and a pint of Whitewine, and let it but juſt boil together; then let it drop thorough a double Brown-paper, and it will be a perfect Sea-Green.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For White.</head>
                  <p>Take of the beſt Cerus, and diſſolve it in ſome of the beſt Iſinglaſs-liquor, and it is done: So muſt you mix all your Colours, as you do uſe them, with ſome of that Liquor, and put them into Gally-pots.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For Yellow.</head>
                  <p>Take Saffron and tie it in a Rag, and put it into ſome of your Liquor; to which you muſt add Gum-Arabick and Fair-water; two parts of Gum, and one of Water: When you uſe them, you muſt warm them, and lay them on with a Pencil, on the wrong-ſide of the Flowers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For Primroſe-Colour.</head>
                  <p>Yellow and White makes it very right: You may make it as Deep or as Pale as you will; ſome will do well a little Deeper than the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:151469:41"/>
                  <head>Fleſh-Colour.</head>
                  <p>Vermillion and White makes Fleſh-Colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Damask-Roſe Colour.</head>
                  <p>Vermillion, and Brazil, and Purple, and White makes the Damaſck-Roſe Colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Graſs-Green.</head>
                  <p>The yellow added to the Sea-Green makes a perfect Graſs-Green, and very beautiful.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Blew.</head>
                  <p>You muſt put in ſome Smalt into your Liquor, and ſtrain it very well; and when you will have it Pale, mix a little White with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Clove-Colour.</head>
                  <p>Take Logwood and boil as you do the Brazil.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Tauney.</head>
                  <p>Mix the Clove-Colour and Red toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To make the Puff-work.</head>
                  <p>Take two ounces of white Vellom cut in pieces, and ſteep it in a pint and half of</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151469:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151469:42"/>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:151469:42"/>
                  <head>Blew.</head>
                  <p>Take Indico and mix with the Spirit of Sack, and when your ſtains are tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough dry, rub them over with White-bread, and wipe it off again with a ſoft clean linnen Cloth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A moſt excellent Black-Dye for any Stuffs or Stockens.</head>
                  <p>Take one peck and half of black Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Bark, and break it indifferently ſmall; then ſteep it three days in three Pails full of water, and if you have any ruſty Iron ſteep it with it; then boil it with a pound of green-Copperus, for the ſpace of an hour and half; if you can get them, put alſo one ounce of Nut-galls beaten to boil with the reſt: then ſcum off all the Bark and let it boil up again; then put your Stuff in which you mean to Dye, and ſtir it down altogether as near as you can, and keep ſtirring of it down for a quarter of an hour; then take it out and drain it, and let it half-dry, then put it in again and do as before; then let it be quite dry, and when it is ſo, waſh it ſo long as it will blaze the Water, then dry it well.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:151469:43"/>
               <head>To make clean Glaſs-Windows.</head>
               <p>Firſt bruſh them with a Cobwebbing-Broom, then take ſome Spaniſh-Whiting and warm Water and waſh them all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver very well, and rub them every where; then waſh it off again with cold Water very well, and rub them with clean Rags till they are very dry.</p>
               <p>And if you would paint the Wooden-barrs of your Windows white or red, take Red-lead, or White-lead, and grind it with a little Linſeed-Oil, and then lay it on with a Bruſh; but firſt you muſt let them be very clean: Do it over twice, but let the firſt be dry before you lay on the ſecond.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make pretty Frames for ſlight Pictures in Black only.</head>
               <p>Cut Paſt-board plain, without form, but only long narrow pieces about two fingers breadth, and faſten them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the corners with a little Glew; then waſh them over with a Bruſh, with a little Lamb-black and Size mixed well together; then preſently before it be dry,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151469:43"/> ſtrew it all over with French-Froſt, of what Colour you pleaſe; then put on ſome Shells with Bees-wax and Roſin melted together hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make Frames for Pictures in work of Satten, Stitch, and the like.</head>
               <p>Let a handſome plain Frame be made of Deal-wood, fit for your piece of Work; then black it over as you did the other, and Froſt it; then have in readineſs ſome Bones out of the Heads of Whitings, Froſted over firſt; do them over with a Feather, with ſome Water wherein Gum-Arabick hath been ſteeped, and put on your Froſt, and let ſome be of one Colour, and ſome of another. Make ſome little Flowers of ſeveral Colours upon round pieces of Cards, with ſmall Satten-Ribbon, and faſten ſome Wier for the ſtalks; get ſome Shells and ſome Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Pearl; ſome Corral and ſome Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; ſome little kinds of Creatures made in Wax, as Frogs, and ſuch like; pieces of old Neck-Laces, and Pendants, with a little Moſs. When you have got all your things ready, put on your Shells firſt in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Fancies with Bees-wax and Roſin,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151469:44"/> and do them quick, and cruſh them on hard; then put on the Mother-pearl, and then as you pleaſe the reſt of the things till you have put on all. It will look like a Frame of great price, but it will not coſt any great matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To adorn a Room with Prints.</head>
               <p>Buy of your Prints only Black and White, of ſorts what are good, and cut them very exactly with a ſmall pair of Ciſſers from the paper, put them into a Book as you do cut them; then let your Room be done with plain Deal, but Wainſcot faſhion, and let it be painted all over with White-lead and Linſeed-Oil, ground together, and ſome little ſtreaks imitating Marble: then lay your Prints upon a ſmooth-board with the wrong-ſides upwards; then with a knife take ſome Gum-Dragon, ſteeped well in fair water, ſpread them all over as thin as you can, and ſtill as you do them, take them up with your knife, and ſo turn them into your hand, and clap them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Wainſcot; but let it be dry firſt; cloſe them well on with your fingers that they be not hollow in any place; and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151469:44"/> obſerve to put them in proper places, or elſe it will be ridiculous; be ſure to put the things flying above, and the walking and creeping things below; let the Houſes and Trees be ſet ſenſibly, as alſo Water with Ships ſailing, as you put them on, obſerve that they have a relation one to another.</p>
               <p>If you employ your fancy well, you may make fine ſtories, which will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry delightful and commendable; alſo Gardens and Forreſts, Landskips, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed any thing you can imagine; for there is not any to be named, but you may find it in Prints, if you go to a Shop that is well ſtored, nor no Pencil can ſhadow more rare than that will ſhew; it makes a Room very lightſome as well as fine: as for thoſe in Colours I do not eſteem for this purpoſe, for they look Childiſhly, and too gay.</p>
               <p>If you mean to make Stories, you muſt buy good ſtore of Figures; the colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ones are good to put upon white Plates and Flower-pots for Cloſets.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:151469:45"/>
               <head>To dreſs up Glaſs-Plates, on which you may lay dry Sweetmeats or Biskets.</head>
               <p>Take your Glaſs-Plates, and lay the right-ſides downward upon a Table; then have in readineſs ſome coloured Prints finely cut, and lay them on with Gum, with their right-ſides to the wrong-ſide of the Plates; then take ſome Spaniſh-Whiting, mixed with Size which is pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleer, let it be as Batter for a Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; order it ſo that there may be no knots in it, but that it may be very ſmooth; then ſpread the ſame all over upon the Prints (not too thick) and when they are very dry, wipe the right-ſide clean, and ſet them up in your Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet to uſe at your pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Fine Hangings for Cloſets.</head>
               <p>Make ſome plain Net with Brown-thread, and a good round Pin; let the Panes be as long and as broad as you think fit; when they are done, waſh them and ſtarch them very ſtiff, and pull them out againſt the fire till they are quite dry, then put one of them into a long Tent, and let it be very ſtreight; then have in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151469:45"/> readineſs a Paper drawn with Leaves, or Flowers and Leaves together, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things you like; tack it at the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners under the Net, and ſo flouriſh it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Paper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make Feathers of Wooſted which do look very like natural Feathers, for the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Beds.</head>
               <p>About four pounds of French-Woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted will ſerve your turn; three pounds of that colour your Bed is wrought with, and one pound of White.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Buy three quarters of a pound of Wier of ſixteen pence the pound; burn it in the fire till it be red-hot; then take it out and cool it, then cut it into pieces; twenty of them muſt be a yard long, and ſixteen ſomething ſhorter, and twelve muſt be but a quarter of a yard long, or little more; double all theſe Wiers in the middle, and twiſt them ſlightly; then take your Wooſted and open it, and cut every skean twice; then comb it well with a Horn-Comb; then cut it in whole locks as it is, in pieces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a quarter of a yard long, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs, and comb every one of them;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151469:46"/> then take three Brown-threds, turn a large Stool the bottom upwards, and tie theſe Brown-threds from one foot of the Stool to the other very ſtreight; then take a long double Brown-thred in a Needle, and then take one of your ſhort locks of Cruel, or Wooſted, and caſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your Threds which you have tied to the Stool; hang them even, then ſew them faſt to the tied ſtring; which that you may the better do, be ſure to hold the ends of the Wooſted in one hand, and ſew with the other; for if you do not ſew the tied Thred faſt in, your Feather will not hold but come to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and one thing you muſt be ſure of, that as you ſew them, to clap another lock on before you have done that you begun, or elſe there will be gaps in your Feathers: In every Feather you muſt put three locks of White, or more if you pleaſe; but not too much in a lock: When you have thus ſewed them, then take your Wiers, faſten a Needle and double Brown-thred to the bolt end of it, and begin at one end of your Woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted you have ſewn, and ſew the Wier very faſt to it; you muſt leave at the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end as much Wier as may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151469:46"/> to bind them up in a Plume, when you have done them all: When you have done thus, then take ſome double white Wooſted, and ſew over all that ſo thick, that nothing may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered that you have done before; then cut the Feather from the tied ſtring, and lay it on your Lap, or a Table, and comb it; then take it by the ſtalk, and with a Bodkin part it as right in the middle as you can; then comb it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, towards the tip, and you will quickly perceive it to look like a natural Feather; then with your Ciſſers cut it in ſhape, and then comb it a little again: the little ones of all muſt be made with Wooſted not above half a quarter of a yard long, for they are for the ſprigs which ſtand up in the middle, and there muſt be three in every ſprig. The twenty large Feathers are for every Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner five, and the other ſixteen are for every Corner four.</p>
               <p>When you bind them up, firſt bind thoſe three together which are for the Sprig, and turn the right-ſides inward; then put on the four with the right-ſides inwards, and then the five; and bind the Wiers very faſt.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:151469:47"/>
               <p> Then put them into the Cups, and turn the Feathers quite back, and bow them down as you would have them be.</p>
               <p>I have given you as full a direction as I can in writing; but you may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that if you were with me but one hour, you would learn perfectly. For theſe kind of Feathers I have taken ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a pound.</p>
               <p>Some count it folly in me to declare ſo many things, and rather wiſh me to keep them ſecret<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but I am of that humour that I muſt and will impart all, what may be beneficial to others; For we are not born for our ſelves alone. God made us to ſerve him, and to keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements; and I am ſure it is part of my duty to be kind to my Neighbour, and what is kindneſs more ſhewed in, than by giving good Counſel, and good Inſtructions; and when we are not near, then to expreſs our ſelves in Writing. So do I do by you all, and do beſeech you to practice what I direct you to.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:151469:47"/>
               <head>How to ſave much work, and to make a ſuit of Chairs which be very noble.</head>
               <p>Let what Draught you pleaſe be drawn upon a very courſe French-Canvas; then have your Chairs cut out as you would have them, either of Camlet or Paragon; put your Stuff into a Tent, and then tack your Canvas ſtreight upon it; ſo work it in Croſ-ſtich, and take heed that you do not cleave the Threds of the Canvas in the working, nor work your Wooſted or Silk too full; and when you have done, cut your Canvas between your Leaves and Flowers, and pluck out every Thred one by one, and there will be your Work very brave upon your Stuff, and will look very high; then form it about with what coloured Gimp you fancy beſt.</p>
               <p>And if you want skill to ſhadow, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Drawer to direct you in the drawing of it; but then you muſt get an Embroiderer to draw it, for no other can direct you right; and you had better not work, then that which is ridiculous.</p>
               <p>This way ſaves the grounding, or cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out to Embroider, and is much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and not common; therefore to be more eſteemed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151469:48"/>
               <head>Another way for Chairs.</head>
               <p>Let your Draught be drawn upon Stuff or Satten, what elſe you pleaſe, and work it with Wooſted or Silk, or both together, which doth better then Silk alone if it be upon Stuff; but if upon Silk, then Silk alone doth beſt: Work it in Satten-ſtich, and as many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtiches as you know, or can deviſe; and when you bring off one ſhadow, take a bright one from another, and that wil much quicken and enliven your work; for one ſhadow ſimply of it ſelf looks very faint: Obſerve when you walk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and find a dead Leaf, or beginning but to wither, how many ſhadows there is mixed together; alſo what Bark of a Tree, what Flie, Worm, or Snail do we admire but thoſe which are extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for their Colours: it is in thoſe things, and as much difference as is between a beautiful Lady and a Cinder Woman (the one hath lovelineſs to their dying hour, the other are never comely) there are alſo ſome Leaves which be of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Graſs-green, ſome Willow, ſome Sea-green, which are in themſelves very
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151469:48"/> pleaſant, and ſome of the dulleſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours you muſt put in, and then your work will ſhew the more naturally; and whatſoever you do, be ſure to let your ſhadow be very dark, for without a dark ſhadow you can make no lively Work.</p>
               <p>Now for the folds of your Leaves or Flowers there muſt be a place for ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, but that muſt be begun with a midling Colour, and fall very light, with ſome other ſhadow among thoſe you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with; but be ſure not to chooſe your Colours too near in ſuch a caſe, but skip a Colour, or ſometimes two, and you will find it very fine work; when you have done one piece, form it about with a Back-ſtich, and let it be purely wrought, and of ſuch a Colour, ſad or light, as may agree with the Leaf or Flower you work: Let the Stalks of all be of one ſhadow, Hair-colour or Aſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>colour will ſuit with any thing.</p>
               <p>You muſt be ſure to ſhadow your Stalks with Black, where you find any part of any thing to lie over it; and in all dark places be ſure to begin your ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow vvith Black.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:151469:49"/>
               <p> This kind of Work I have wrought often upon Demities; and have wrought thereon with Wooſted, Cruel, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hair, in all ſorts of Stiches; all kinds of Shadows, and many fancies which were after my own fancy, not at all to imitate others; for there is nothing which I hate more, than to work as a Child doth after a Sampler: That brain that can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent nothing, is good for nothing; nor there is nothing which I more love than Invention.</p>
               <p>One Bed thus wrought, with Chairs belonging to it, is worth a hundred Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies before the Upholſterer comes to touch it; and may, if it be cleanly wrought, be uſed ſeveral years before it be waſhed; as hath been proved.</p>
               <p>It will not be amiſs to give you ſome directions for the waſhing of it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Make a ſtrong ladder with Soap and good Water, reaſonable warm; then lay one of your Curtains upon a Table, and with a Bruſh and ſome of this lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, rub it very well all over, and do ſo ill three Ladders are ſpent; then pour on good ſtore of fair Water to Rinſe it very well; then hang it to dry from the Sun, with the wrong-ſide outward, and as it
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151469:49"/> dries, pluck it out and ſmooth it, and fold it up, and then hang it out again, and ſo do till it be quite dry: There is no Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour but will hold, if you do waſh it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner; but if you do rub the Soap upon it, that will change the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</p>
               <p>The beſt Lining for theſe Beds is changable Sarſnet, or Ducape, for that will agree with any of your ſhadows, and it is as cheap as any thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To embroider Petty-coats, Bodices, or Belts.</head>
               <p>When your Pattern is drawn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> form it about with black Gimp, or other, which you do fancy beſt, and fill the Leaves and under-parts of the Flowers with Saxen-ſtich, ſome dark and ſome lighter: then for the upper-parts, and ſeeds of Flowers, let them be done with high-work, as Purple-ſtich, and ſuch like, and let your ſtalks be all alike with a great Gimp twiſted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> your Flowers may be of all manner of Shadows as you fancy; and if you ſhadow them well, they will look very naturally. Thus you may go fine, and with leſs coſt than if you bought good Lace.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:151469:50"/>
               <p> It is more commendable a great deal to wear ones own Work, than to be made fine vvith the Art of others; and though one may be envied for it, yet none can have ſo juſt a quarrel againſt them, becauſe it is their Ingenuity; and beſides it argues that Perſon not to be idle, but rather a good Houſe-wife. Any fool may be made fine with Coſt, but give me thoſe who can be neat and nobly habited with but a reaſonable charge. The World is grown very fine of late years, but it is with ſo much charge (together with ſo ill a phanſie ſome have in chooſing things) that they look more like Stage-players than fit to come into any Church, or Civil places: Some will plead Ignorance, not knowing how to do theſe things, but that's a bare Excuſe; for if they know not already, they may learn: In a Weeks time I dare undertake to teach any Ingenious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Embroider any of theſe things; therefore if any of you have a deſire to Learn, I ſhall be willing to wait on you at your Houſes, and to teach you and your Servants; and for my Work, what I ſhall do, and for Teaching of you, I ſhall expect four ſhillings the day, and, I
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151469:50"/> hope, you vvill judge it reaſonable: for you may imagine, that the mean while I am with you, I am wholly ſequeſtred from all profits and benefits which might happen. Likewiſe if any Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman would learn to Preſerve, if ſhe pleaſe to give me forty ſhillings in hand, ſhe ſhall have the liberty to come ſo oft as ſhe pleaſes, and bring her mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials with her; and at any time if there be any new thing to be learned, at any time, for ſeven years, I will direct her, or give her a Receipt, if at diſtance.</p>
               <p>I think it will not be amiſs if I give you ſome direction what ſtitches to put into a Bed which is wrought only with one Colour, therefore obſerve this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing:</p>
               <p>Form it all with a double Back-ſtitch, and on the one ſide of the Stalks work a broad Gold-ſtitch, and bring it off by degrees with powdering, firſt pretty big ſtitches, and ſo ſmaller and ſmaller; work the veins of the leaves with Bread-ſtitch, Chain-ſtitch, open Chain-ſtitch, and any other that you can think on, or deviſe; then ſprig them thick with ſeveral Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and let the folds of your Leaves be the thinneſt work, and be ſure you put a ſhadow under every fold.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:151469:51"/>
               <p> If your leaves be great, let them be the fuller of Work, or elſe you had as good do nothing; for how will the Ground ſhew if the work be too thin.</p>
               <p>I ſaw a very fine Bed once wrought in this manner following:</p>
               <p>The Ground was an Aſh-colour Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon, and drawn all over vvith Clouds, ſome of one ſort, ſome of another, and wrought to reſemble the Clouds of Night; ſome very dark, ſome lighter, and here and there between were Stars, made vvith oyes, vvhich you muſt be ſure to have them good, or elſe they vvill change; elſe they vvill hold as long as your other vvork will laſt.</p>
               <p>I have often been deſired to give ſome directions for Work in Print, and truly I have ſo done as plain as I can: I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh I could infuſe all that I can do, into thoſe vvho are deſirous to learn; it vvould do them good, and me no harm; for I am ſtill, and ſhall be all my life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time improving my ſelf: and ſtill as I do purchaſe new things, I ſhall impart them to you.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now give you ſomething of Cookery, and ſuch as hath not yet been Printed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:151469:51"/>
               <head>Imprimis: <hi>To pot Fowl to carry to Sea; or to keep to be ſpent in your Houſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a good company of Duck and Mallard, pluck them, and draw them, and lay them in a Tub with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Pepper and Salt for twenty four hours; then truſs them and roaſt them; and when they are roſted let them drain from their Gravy, for that will make them corrupt; then put them handſomly into a Pot, and take the Fat which came from them in the roaſting, and good ſtore of Butter, and melt together in a pot, ſet into a Kettle of boiling-water, put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in good ſtore of Cloves bruiſed a little, ſome ſliced Nutmeg, Mace, Bay-leaves, and Salt, and let them ſtew in the Butter a while; then while it is hot pour it over your Fowls in the Pot, and let the Pot be filled, ſo that the Fowls may be cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; then lay a Trencher in upon them, and keep them down with a vveight or ſtone till they are cold; then take of the ſame kind of Spice which you did put into your Butter, beat it very fine, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151469:52"/> ſtrew over it, and lay ſome Bay-leaves on the top, ſo cover it up; they will keep a good while. Drain your Fowl from the Gravy twenty four hours before you put them into your Pot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very fine way to pot Neats-Tongues.</head>
               <p>Take the largeſt Neats-Tongues you can get, and Salt them very well; two days after pour away the bloody-Brine, and Salt them again, and let them lie in that Salt a Month; then take ſome Salt-Peter, and a little Roach-Allom beaten together, and rub them over with that, and let them lie one Week; then boil them till they be tender, with ſome Hay on the top of them, then take them out of the Kettle, and pull off the skins; then hang them up in a Chimney where Wood is burnt for four daies and nights: then melt ſome Butter with Spice, as you do for the Potted-fowl, and put your Tongues in a Pot, and pour that over them; and when they have been Potted one Month, take out one, and eat it with Muſtard and Sugar, or Muſtard alone. Theſe will look very red, and eat plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:151469:52"/>
               <head>To boil Beef or Mutton to eat ſavourly.</head>
               <p>Take any piece of good Beef, and ſet it on the fire with as much water as will cover it; put in ſuch a quantity of Salt as you think fit; let it boil, and ſcim it very well; then put in a little whole Pepper, Lemmon-pill, a blade or two of Mace, ſome ſliced Nutmeg, a few Cloves, and a little Time and Winter-Savory; ſo let them ſtew together cloſe covered upon a ſlow-fire till your Meat begin to be tender; then put in good ſtore of Herbs, as Perſley, Spinage, Lettice, Chervil, Radiſh-tops, Sorrel, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Herb you love: and when the Herbs are boiled, and the Meat thoroughly ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, put ſome ſliced Bread into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Diſh, and lay your Meat on it, then pour your Broth thereon, and ſerve it to the Table: One drop of this Broth will be better than twenty which is made the plain way.</p>
               <p>If they vvho are to eat it do love O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or Shelot, it will do very well to put ſome in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:151469:53"/>
               <head>To Boil, or rather to Stew a Leg of Veal; a very ſavory Diſh.</head>
               <p>Take a large white Leg of Veal, and ſtuff it with ſome fat Bacon and Sage ſhred ſmall together, with a little Sage and Nutmeg; cover it with Water, put in ſome Salt, let it boil, and ſcim it well; then put in ſome ſweet Herbs, and ſome Spice, ſuch as you love, and let it boil leiſurely cloſe covered; then when you find that the Knuckle begins to be tender, put in a pound of Sauſages cut one by one, and let them ſtew with it for a while; when you find it is enough, put in a piece of freſh Butter, and ſerve it in with the Broth upon ſliced Bread, and lay the Sauſages on the top: Garniſh the Diſh with Collops of Bacon and Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To fry Clary the beſt way.</head>
               <p>Take the Yolks and White of Eggs beaten together very well; then put a little grated Nutmeg, and beaten Cinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon therein; then having your Butter very hot in the Frying-pan, take a Leaf by the ſtalk end and dip it therein, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151469:53"/> lay it into the Pan, and ſo another as faſt as you can, till your Pan be full; fry them brown with a very quick fire, and ſerve them in with a little Butter: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not a little Salt amongſt your Eggs when you beat them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To dreſs a Legg of Mutton; a very ſavory Diſh.</head>
               <p>Boil your Mutton in Water and Salt for the ſpace of an hour; then cut it in thin ſlices, and put it into a Diſh over a Chaffing-diſh of Coals, without any Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, and in a little time you will find the Gravy will be Liquor enough; then put in a little Salt, and a little grated Nutmeg, one Onion, or two or three Shelots ſliced, a ſprig of Time, and Winter-ſavory, and one Anchovy; let<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it ſtew between two Diſhes till it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt enough; then put in a piece of freſh Butter, and when it hath ſtewed a little longer, take it up and ſerve it in: Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh your Diſh with pickled Barberries, and pickled Oyſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:151469:54"/>
               <head>To ſtew Muſcles, or Cockles.</head>
               <p>Take any of them, and waſh them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, and put them into boiling Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Salt, and let them boil till they gape; then take them up, and take them out of their ſhells, and put them into a Diſh over a Chaffing-diſh of Coals with a little Whitewine, a blade or two of Mace, and a little Nutmeg and whole Pepper; let them ſtew a while; then put in a piece of Butter and ſhake them together; then put your Fiſh into a hot Diſh, and take the yolks of two or three Eggs well beaten, and thicken the Sauce vvith them over the fire; you muſt let them be but a little time over the fire, and ſtir it vvell for fear it turn. Garniſh your Diſh vvith Perſley, Salt, and pickled Barberries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To ſtew Parſnips: A good Diſh.</head>
               <p>Boil the tendereſt Parſnips very well, then ſcrape them very clean, and cut them in two, and then ſlit them in half; put them in a Diſh vvith ſome White vvine, vvhole Mace, grated Nutmeg, and a little
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151469:54"/> Salt; vvhen they have ſtewed cloſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered one hour, then put in ſome pieces of Marrow, and a little Sugar; then ſtew them very vvell, and a little before you take them up, put in a little Butter, and ſhake them vvell together, and ſerve them in. Garniſh your Diſh vvith thin ſlices of boiled Parſnip, and fine Sugar beaten and ſearced.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a good Pye of Beef.</head>
               <p>Take of the tendereſt piece of Beef, and cut it in thin ſlices, and beat it very vvell vvith a Rouling-pin, and lay it in a little quantity of Claret-vvine all night, vvith a little grated Nutmeg, and crack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Pepper; in the Morning make your Pye, and lay ſome Butter in the bottom; then lay in your Meat, but firſt Salt it a little; then lay ſome more Butter on the top, and pour in that Wine in vvhich it lay, and ſo cloſe it up, and let it Bake three hours, or more: So ſerve it in hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:151469:55"/>
               <head>To dreſs red Beet-Roots.</head>
               <p>Waſh them and boil them very well, ſlice them in round ſlices, and eat them with Butter, Vinegar and Salt; and you may if you pleaſe eat them cold with Oyl, and Vinegar and Salt; it is a very pleaſant Sallad.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a good Pidgeon Pye.</head>
               <p>Pluck your Pidgeons very well; then cut them in halves, waſh them and dry them; cleanſe their Livers and Gizzards alſo, and let them go with them; ſeaſon them with Pepper, Salt, and Nutmeg; When your Pye is raiſed, lay in ſome Butter in the bottom, then lay in your Pidgeons, with the cut-ſide downward<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and then the Yolks of hard Eggs, and a little Time ſtripped from the Stalks; then lay on ſome more Butter on the top, and put in a glaſs-full of Claret-wine: So lid your Pye, and let it bake one Hour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:151469:55"/>
               <head>To boil a Cock, and to make good Broth with him.</head>
               <p>Pluck and draw your Fowl, waſh him very vvell, and bruiſe his Leggs; boil him in a little Water and Salt for one hour; then add ſome Water wherein Mutton hath been boiled, and put in a quarter of a pound of French-Barley, or Rice, which you pleaſe, with ſome Time, Winter-ſavory, and a little Lemmon-pill, a little large Mace and ſliced Nutmeg, with a Clove or two.</p>
               <p>When it is clean ſcummed, let it only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ew till it be enough; then take up the Cock for a while, and boil the Broth very well; then put him in again and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat him throughly; then ſerve it to the Table, and garniſh your diſh with Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non and Barberries.</p>
               <p>Be ſure to truſs your Fowl handſomly. This Diſh is very good for Weak Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To boil a Fore-Loyn of Pork, with good Sauce to it.</head>
               <p>Let your Pork be reaſonably well ſalted, and boil it very well; then have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> readineſs a good quantity of Sorrel
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151469:56"/> ſtripped from the Stalks, and beaten in a Mortar as fine as poſſible you can, then put in a few Crumbs of Bread, the yolks of hard Eggs, vvith a little Muſtard, and a little Salt: and ſo ſerve in your Pork vvith this Sauce, and garniſh your Diſh vvith Perſley, or any other Green Leaves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To ſtew Rabbits.</head>
               <p>When they are flea'd cut them in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and put them into a Pot vvith as much Water as vvill vvell cover them; put in ſome Salt and let them boil, and ſcum them vvell, then put in a faggot of Sweet-herbs, and let them ſtevv cloſe covered; then pill a good quantity of great Onions, and boil them in ſeveral Waters till they be tender; put them alſo into the Pot vvith your Rabbits, and let them ſtevv till the Rabbits be very tender: a little before you take them up, put in a good quantity of freſh But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a little Vinegar, and ſtir it about very vvell; and then Diſh them for the Table, and garniſh your Diſh vvith O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, Salt, and green Leaves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:151469:56"/>
               <head>To boil Green-Peaſe.</head>
               <p>When they are ſheal'd put them into a long Gally-pot, and ſet it into a Pot of Seething-vvater, and cover the Gally-pot very vvell, and in a ſhort time you vvill find the Peaſe to be fine and tender; then put them out into a Diſh, and ſtrew ſome Salt upon them, and put in a good quantity of Butter, and ſo ſhake them vvell betvven tvvo Diſhes; then put them into a hot Diſh, and ſerve them to the Table. If they vvho are to eat them do love Sparemint, put in a ſprigg into the Pot vvith them.</p>
               <p>Theſe are far more pleaſant and ſvveet, then thoſe vvhich are boiled in Water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To preſerve Green-Peaſe a while.</head>
               <p>When they are ſheal'd and pickt, put them into a long Gally-pot, and take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome Butter, and cover them vvith it, and cloſe it down upon them vvith your and; your Butter muſt not be melted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut cold; then cover your Pot very vvell and ſet it in a cool place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:151469:57"/>
               <head>To dreſs Old Beans.</head>
               <p>Lay them in Water one Night; then put them into cold Water, and ſet them over the fire, and let them heat by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; and when they are hot, let them boil apace, and with them a piece of Bacon, and ſome Perſley; when they are very tender take them up, and drain them well from the Water; pour ſome Butter melted very thick over them, and lay Bacon on each ſide of them, and ſerve them to the Table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To dreſs Old French-Beans.</head>
               <p>Water them as you do the other Old Beans, and boil them after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but no Bacon with them, and when they are enough, take them up, and drain them well from the Water; ſtrew ſome Salt and grated Nutmeg on them, and Butter them well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:151469:57"/>
               <head>To ſtew Beef, a very fine way.</head>
               <p>Slice your Beef in thin ſlices, and put it into a long Gally-pot, with a ſliced O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſome Pepper, and ſome Salt, and ſweet Herbs, with a little Perſley; cover the Pot cloſe, and ſet it in a Kettle of ſeething water; ſo let it be ten or twelve hours, and put in a little Clarret Wine alſo.</p>
               <p>Let the fire be well tended under the Kettle, and you will find a dainty Diſh of it.</p>
               <p>Your meat muſt be reaſonable Fat: Serve it to the Table upon ſippets of White-bread.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make rare Pyes of a Calves-Head.</head>
               <p>Take a fine fat Calves-Head, and cleanſe it well; boil it with Water and Salt till it be very tender; then take it from the Bones and mince it very ſmall; then to a pound of this Meat, take one pound of Currans, waſhed and picked very well, one pound of Raiſons of the Sun, a little Salt, ſome Nutmeg, Cloves, Mace, and Cinnamon beaten fine, a little
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151469:58"/> Whitewine, and a little Lemmon-pill ſhred ſmall, with a little Sugar, and the yolks of four hard Eggs; having your Pye ready raiſed lay Butter in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; then put in your minc'd Meat, and on the top of it lay ſome pieces of Marrow, and ſome Dates cut in thin ſlices, then lay Butter over that, and lid it and bake it; and when it is baked, cut open the Lid, and put in a little Whitewine, Butter and Sugar. This is a very good Pye, and may be eaten hot or cold.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a Pudding of cold Meat.</head>
               <p>Take any pieces of cold Meat, which is not fit to come to the Table any more, as Veal, Mutton, Lamb, Capon, Chicken, Rabbit, or the like; mince either of theſe very ſmall, and put ſome Milk to it, and the yolks and whites of Eggs, with ſome beaten Spice and Salt, and a little Sugar; make it up with a little Flower, ſo that you may wrap it in a piece of thin Paſte; put it into boiling water, and let it boil two or three hours; then take it up and put it into a Diſh, and ſo cut it in ſlices, and Butter it; ſtrew
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151469:58"/> Sugar on your Diſh and ſerve it in. This may be called <hi>The good Houſ-wives Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are fools who cannot tell what to do with ſcraps of Meat: (Are they any worſe than the reſt?) If any be too Fat, let them try it up for Suet, elſe make a Florentine or Pudding with it; and ſo uſed, you may bring it (if occaſion were) before a Great Perſon. It is an eaſie matter here for any that hath Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, if they have nothing but cold Meat in the Houſe, to go to the Market and buy a Joynt of Meat: But, I pray, what do they in other Countries, where they have not ſuch plenty? Do they not live upon green Herbs, Plants and Roots, as much as any kind of Meat? And who are ſo weak as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> People? for they eat ſo much of Meat, that they diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per themſelves with it: whereas if they did eat Herbs, Roots and Plants more freely, it would be better for them. Obſerve the Diet of the <hi>French, Italian, Dutch, Spaniards, Portugals,</hi> or any other Nation; they make good ſavory Meat, and do not ſpend half ſo much Meat as we do; yet, who ſo ſtrong as they? you ſhall hardly ever ſee a Crooked
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151469:59"/> perſon among a thouſand of them, nor weak ey'd, ſo far as to give blemiſh to them; and I do impute that to their Diet partly: And that they do not Coat their Children too ſoon, when they are young, but keep them long in their Blankets; that prevents the Rickets, and many other Diſtempers: but our proud Nurſes here muſt be humour'd, although it be to the ruine of a Child; but if there were none would humour them more than I, they would be mute. Let them look well to a Child, and keep it ſweet and clean, and then if they have their Wages duly paid them, they have no reaſon to find fault: If the Child do not go ſo fine as they would have it, it will be the Parents ſhame, not theirs. It is better to let a Child, or ones ſelf go plain, than to run in Debt for fine Cloaths. They that will heed what I ſay, I believe it will do no harm, but a great deal of good, for they will find it true what I ſay.</p>
               <p>Did I not ſee what fools we are made, here in England, both by our Nurſes and Servants, and what deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction there is made in many Houſes, I ſhould not ſpeak; but really there is in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151469:59"/> ſome Houſes, I know, ſo much Waſte, as that it is a great ſhame and diſcredit to thoſe who guide the Family; and if they would look a little more into their Affairs, they would be more careful for the future.</p>
               <p>Therefore all you who are Miſtreſſes of Families, look narrowly to your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and let them not ſpoil or waſte your Goods, for which you muſt take pains and care: Be watchful that they do not ſit up beyond their uſual time, Juncketing, and making their Friends welcome (as they call them) with your Goods; while you are aſleep, and think no harm of them. Suffer not your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to go too frequently abroad with Servants, leaſt it cauſe ſuch an obligation, as you ſhall pay dearly for the Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</p>
               <p>If you ſee your Servant go beyond what you think the Wages you allow her will well maintain, and to lay up ſomewhat in caſe of Sickneſs, or being out of Service, you ought to Queſtion her, or him; for either they muſt run in Debt, or Cheat you, or take ſome ill Courſe to maintain their pride and folly; and then of neceſſity diſcredit muſt follow:
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151469:60"/> On the other ſide; If you find a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to be Civil, neat, cleanly, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to pleaſe, I do adviſe ſuch a Servant may be cheriſhed and encouraged, not only by good Words, but good Gifts alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for ſuch a Servant cannot be too highly prized: yet too much of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity I do not hold with, for that will breed much Contempt. Keep your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as you being her Superiour, and ſhew your love and favour in what may benefit her.</p>
               <p>Truſt not a Servant too much with Secrets which concern your Credit, or your Livelyhood, leaſt you thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave your ſelf to them; for I have ſeen very ſad effects from ſuch confidings. You may make the Meſſengers for to carry Letters, but do not truſt them to be your Counſellours.</p>
               <p>If any Servant, who hath performed her Duty to you, do ask your advice in Marriage, give her the beſt Counſel you can, and alſo beſtow ſomewhat towards the forwarding of it: If you probably think ſhe may be happy, let the Man who ſhe hath an inclination to, know that you have a Kindneſs for her, and that you will ſhew them all the Favour
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151469:60"/> you can; if they will endeavour honeſtly to live in the World.</p>
               <p>If your ability will reach to it, be kind to them upon their Wedding-day; either to give them their Meat, or at leaſt wiſe, to give them ſomewhat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Charges: And when ſhe is gone from you, afford her your aſſiſtance when ſhe ſtands in need, and grace her with your Company when it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; for then her Husband will be apt to be the more kind to her, and will have an awful reverence for you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Nurſes.</head>
               <p>If you find an ill one, take your Child away, and own her no more. Let your ſilence be her ſorrow, and her ſhame: Report not ill of her, leaſt it be her Ruine; neither Commend her, leaſt you ruine your own Credit. It is better to be ſilent, and let others find her out, then for you to accuſe her: It is enough, that you have taken your Child away.</p>
               <p>If you find a good and faithful Nurſe, one who hath done her duty to you in the care for the Child, cheriſh her, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh her, and never think any thing too
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151469:61"/> much that you can do for her, without prejudice to your ſelf: If ſhe hath been careful of the Childs Cloaths, give her what you can well ſpare of them for her own Child, or elſe give her the worth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of them to lay out her ſelf; and as your Child grows up, teach it to love the Nurſe, and infuſe thoſe Principles into it, that when you are dead and gone, your Child may ſtill remember her with a perpetual kindneſs. This is my own mind: I would have my Children do ſo, and therefore I commend theſe Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to others.</p>
               <p>For Preſerving I have before given you very many Receipts, and of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beſt, for all manner of things; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt not expect that I ſhall ſay much as to that Art; yet ſome things there be which you have not, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; and a mixture of things, ſuch as commeth into my mind, that I have not yet written.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:151469:61"/>
               <head>Imprimis: <hi>To make very fine Bisket.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke one pound of the yolks of hard Eggs, one pound of the fineſt Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar beaten and ſearced, two ounces of candid Iringo-root, one ounce of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Cittrou-pill, the whites of two Eggs well beaten, one quarter of an ounce of Cinnamon beaten fine, one Nutmeg grated, half a quarter of an ounce of beaten Ginger; beat all theſe in a Mortar to a Paſte, with a little Sack, and one grain of Amber-greaſe; then mould it up with ſearced Sugar; make it into little Cakes, according to your fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and lay them upon Wafer ſheets, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Tin-plate, and bake them after Bread is drawn.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another ſort of Bisket.</head>
               <p>Take half a pound of Naples-Bisket, mix them with a little Sack, when you have ſliced them thin, and let them lye in ſoak in it; then take half a pound of ſweet Almonds blanched in cold Water,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151469:62"/> and beaten to a Paſte with a little fair<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Water, to keep them from oyling; then beat that Paſte with the Naples Bisket, and the Yolks of three Eggs, and the Whites of one: when you have mixed them, then put in three quarters of a pound of ſearced Sugar, a little juyce of Lemmon, and one grain of Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greace; of what Spice you like, you may put in a little beaten and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
               <p>When theſe are well incorporated, take them out of the Mortar, and mould it up with ſearced Sugar, upon a ſmooth Board, and make it into what form you pleaſe; bake them upon Waſer-ſheets on tin Plates after-Brown-bread is drawn: do not take them from the Plates till they are cold enough,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make Sirrop of Violets.</head>
               <p>Pick your Violets very clean, and beat them well in a Mortar; then ſtrain them, and to one pint of the juyce take one quarter of a pint of Spring-water; put it into the Mortar with the ſtamped Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets which you have ſtrained, ſtamp
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151469:62"/> them together a while, and ſtrain the Water well from them, and mix them with your other juyce; then put it into a long Gally-pot, and to each pint of Juyce put in one pound of double Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſined Sugar; let it ſtand cloſe covered for the ſpace of twelve hours; then put in a little quantity of Juyce of Lemmon, that will make it look purely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; then ſet your Gally-pot into a Kettle of ſeething-water covered, till you find it to be thick enough; then ſet it by till it is cold, and then put it up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sirrop of Roſes, a good way.</head>
               <p>Fill a great Stone-pot with Damask-Roſe leaves, as hard as you can thruſt it; then fill it up with Damask-Roſe water, and cover it with Stone or Glaſs, and ſet it into a Kettle of boiling Water, till you find that the Roſe-water be very well coloured, which may be about four hours; then ſtrain it out hard, and put the Liquor into a Gally-pot, and to every pint of it, put two pounds of Sugar; then cover the Pot
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151469:63"/> and ſet it into a Kettle of ſeething Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let it ſtand till it be a thick Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup: when it is cold put it up and keep it for your uſe; it will worke very kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and very effectually.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The beſt way to preſerve Fruits.</head>
               <p>Wet the Sugar for them with the juyce of ſome of the ſame Fruit, inſtead of Water, and that will give a full and lively taſte, and they will keep the better: The worſt of your Fruit will ſerve for that.</p>
               <p>Be pleaſed to obſerve my former Books for the ordering of all Fruits in the Preſerving, only do not put in Roſe-water ſo generally, as is ſet down, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not ſo much uſed as formerly, unleſs in Cordial things, or ſome other particular things; therefore where it is liked uſe it, or elſe not, for we have new Modes for Eating and Drinking, as well as for Apparel: One cannot ſo ſtrictly ſet down any thing, but that in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Sauce; dreſſing of Meat, with Seaſoning, Preſerving ſeveral things, and the like, there muſt be a judgment in thoſe who order them, to leave out, or
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151469:63"/> to add, or elſe they will pleaſe but a few pallets<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for ſome do hate the taſte of what others do extreamly love.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make very fine Jelly for a weak ſtomach.</head>
               <p>Take Calves-Feet, or Sheeps-Trotters cleanly dreſſed, and ſplit them in half; put them into a Pipkin with as much Whitewine as will cover them, put in a little Salt, make it boil, and ſcum it well; then put in a blade or two of whole Mace, with a ſprig or two of Time, and a little Lemmon-pill, put in a few Dates ſliced very thin; cover it cloſe, and let it boil leiſurely till the Feet be very tender; then take them up, and eat them if you pleaſe; and take the Liquor and ſtrain it, and to a quart of it put in the juyce of one Lemmon, and as much fine Sugar as will well ſweeten it, and ſet it over the fire till the Sugar be throughly melted; then keep it in a Gally-pot, and give the Party of it three or four times in a day, as much as they pleaſe to take; if you like it, you may put in a little Ambergreace and Roſe-water<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the one is pleaſing and good for a weak ſtomach, the other for the Brain;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151469:64"/> Amber-greace is good for the Head (if inwardly taken) but it is not good to ſmell to, becauſe it will raiſe fumes to the head: Yet obſerve this, I once did ask a Phyſician concerning Musk and Ambergreace, Why the ſmell of either of them did offend ſo much? He An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me thus; <q>The reaſon (ſaith he) why either of them are ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>five, is, becauſe they ſmell but a little, and do only diſturb; but if they go into a Shop where ſtore is, and ſmell to divers pounds of it, they will find it rather a purge downward, than a raiſer of Fumes to the Head.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To Candy White Sugar; excellent good for any Cough or Cold.</head>
               <p>Take two pounds of the beſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Sugar, and put it in a Diſh to dry very well in a warm Oven; then beat it fine and ſearce it; mix with this quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, one ounce of the beſt prepared Amber; mingle them very well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and put them into a Preſerving-Pan, with one pint of Fair-water; melt it over a gentle fire, and when it boils,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151469:64"/> put in the White of an Egg to clarifie it; then ſeum it very well, and when you perceive it to be as clear as Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal, then let it ſtand in the Pan until it be cold, covered very cloſe: then take fair Running-water about two quarts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and one ounce of the cleareſt Roch-Allom beaten to powder, mix them together, and let them ſtand twenty four hours: When you have ſo done, take an Earthen-Veſſel, or Pot, and ſome few ſticks of the whiteſt ſappy-Fire, ſplintered from un-wrought Deal, and place your ſticks as you do in a Bee-Hive; croſs every way, ſet this Pot over a few Embers empty; then mix your Sugar and your Water in your Preſerving-Pan, ſetting them upon the fire; and ſo ſoon as you perceive the Sugar to ſink, then pour out the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, having a Cullender<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; pour your Sugar into the ſaid Pot very gently through the Cullender, and it will Candy preſently in ſquare forms, and that which falleth to the bottom will be as good as the reſt, though perhaps not altogether ſo clear of colour; as ſoon as you have poured in all your Sugar, which will rope like Hony; then ſtop
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151469:65"/> your Pot very cloſe, and let the Pot ſtand in a Veſſel of cold water four daies very well luted; they uſually break the Pot when they take the Candy; then break it off the ſticks, and keep it in a Box in ſome dry place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A moſt rare Receipt for the Scurvy; for old Catarrhs or Rheums; or for a Conſumption.</head>
               <p>Take a good quantity of Scurvy-graſs, and beat it, and ſtrain it; take the juyce thereof and ſet it over the fire till it be hot, but let it not boil; ſo ſoon as you ſee a thick ſcum ariſe, take it off, and ſtrain it through a linnen Cloth, but never preſs it between your fingers; as ſoon as the ſcum is thrown away, then ſet it over the fire again, and take clarified Hony three ounces, Butter clarified with three Cloves of Garlick one ounce, Anniſeeds half an ounce, Eunulacampane half an ounce, Liquoriſh half an ounce, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered very fine, and ſearced through a lawn Sieve, Saffron one dram finely beaten, White Sugar-Candy finely beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en one ounce; mix all theſe powders
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151469:65"/> very well together, and ſtrew them carefully into the aforeſaid Juyce, with the clarified Butter and Hony, and keep it continually ſtirring till you have incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated it fully over the fire; then take it from the fire, and keep it ſtirring till it be cold: then if you have a mind to keep it for a Sirrop, you may keep it in a Gally-pot, or you may make it thicker with more Sugar-Candy; add a little F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os Sulphuris, and you may perfume them if you pleaſe; that is, if you ſtiffen it enough for Lozenges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent Medicine for any Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.</head>
               <p>Take a quarter of a peck of fine Wheat-flower, half an ounce of Cloves beaten very fine, two Nutmegs, and a quarter of an ounce of Mace beaten fine, mix theſe well with the Flower; as alſo half a pound of fine Sugar beaten and ſearced; put in ſome juyce of Harts-tongue and Liver-wort, the yolks of ſix Eggs, and ſix ounces of freſh ſweet Butter, knead it together very well, and make it into a Cake, and bake it with
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151469:66"/> Bread; eat of it very often and no doubt you will find good of it, for it hath done very great Cures upon many who were Obſtructed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Here is a moſt excellent Plaiſter, which is called the</hi> Catholick, <hi>and for fear I ſhould forget it, I will not omit it any any longer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take of Roſin beaten beaten to powder two pounds and a half, Heifers Tallow one pound and a quarter, tryed with a gentle fire and cleanſed; when it is cold ſcrape away the droſs from the bottom, and melt it in a Braſs Veſſel; then ſtrew in the Roſin by handfuls, and ſtir it with a Willow Spatula, continually ſtirring it until it be all ſtirred in and melted; then have ready a Baſon of Pewter, and in it of Water of Camomile, of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Briony-Root, and of Damask Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, of each eight ounces, with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Salt of Wormwood, Salt of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, Salt of Scurvy-graſs, Vitriol cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonate, of each one ounce and half; then pour in the melted bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d ſtir it with the Spatula from the Eaſt to the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151469:66"/> Weſt, round continually, until the body have ſeemingly ſwallowed up all the Waters and Salt; continue it ſtirring until the Water appear, and thus work it until the body be as white as Snow; then let it ſtand a Month in the Water, covered from duſt; and when you uſe it, let it not come near any fire, but work a little at a time, until it be as white as Snow on the brawn of your hand, over againſt the little-Finger; ſpread it on a linnen-Cloth or Leather, for the beſt <hi>Catholick</hi> Plaiſter in the World; for the Reins in all Accidents; for all Bruiſes and great Contuſions, and where the Bones are broken into ſmall bits, to eaſe pains<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leaſt a Gangrene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue; then twice a day foment the part with hot ſtroops wrung out of a fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, made with a ſtrong Lye of three quarts made with Wood-Aſhes, then in the Lye Centaury, St. <hi>Johns</hi> Wort, Mallows, Wormwood, of each a good handful, one root of <hi>Solomons</hi> Seal, if you can get one, or elſe it may be made without foment with hot ſtroops wrung out of this liquor of Wollen Cloaths, and apply to the part as hot as may be, and cover it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Blankets to keep in the heat,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151469:67"/> and before it be quite cold, renew ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hot ſtroop; continue this order one hour Morning and Evening, then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently apply the Plaiſter a little warmed every time; when you ſee want, ſpread it again if you ſee cauſe. But when ſuch ſhatterings are of Bones, Contuſed Wounds, Diſlocations; roul it not up as other fractures, but have a Box made open at each end, and lay the part on a pillow, and let the ſtrings of binding come about the pillow, and lay the Member in the Box; bind it not hard, and ſometimes not at all. This is a very great Secret, and to be valued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make fine Jelly of Fruit, which will look tranſparent.</head>
               <p>Take ſome Iſinglaſs and break it in little bits, and boil it in Water very well, and ſtrain it; then colour it with any ſort of Fruit, by putting in the juyce thereof; then to every pint of it take one pound of the beſt refined Sugar, boil them together, and ſcum it very well; and when you find it to be enough, put it into flat Glaſſes, and keep it in a Cub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bord.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:151469:67"/>
               <p> You may make Jelly of any Cordial Herb or Flower in this manner, which will be very comfortable and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, and alſo very pleaſant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A pretty ſweet Meat of Lettuce-ſtalks.</head>
               <p>Boil them in ſeveral Waters till they are tender, then waſh them in cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and dry them well, then take their weight in fine Sugar, juſt wet it with Water, and boil it to a Candy-height; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen put in your ſtalks, being firſt ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in a Mortar very well; boil them together till it be very cleer, and take them from the fire, and put them into Glaſſes; and if you pleaſe you may add <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> little juyce of a Lemmon to it as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oils, and a little candid pill of a Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ſhred ſmall, for that will give a good taſte, and make it look very beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful.</p>
               <p>In like manner you may do with Harty-Choaks bottoms, when they are boiled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ender.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:151469:68"/>
               <head>To make Marmalade of Damſons.</head>
               <p>Take your Damſons and ſcald them in Water till the skins do crack; then pill them, and take away the Stones; then beat them well in a Mortar; then take their weight in fine Sugar, wet it with Water, and boil it to a Candy-height; then put in your Damſons, and boil it, and keep it ſtirring continually, till it will come from the bottom of the Poſnet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make Sirrop of Snails; moſt admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in Conſumptions.</head>
               <p>Take ſhell-Snails, and break their ſhells off, and waſh them very well in a Pan with Water and Salt, and then with ſeveral Waters alone till they be very clean; then put them into a long Gally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot, with a blade or two of Mace, and a little quantity of Whitewine; cover the Pot, and ſet it into a Kettle of boiling Water, for the ſpace of two hours or more; then put them out into an Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocras Bag, and hang them up to drain, and let them drop into a Glaſs with a mouth ſo wide as that it may not drop beſides, and when it hath dropped all it will; then to a pint of it take a pound of White Sugar Candy, two ſpoonfuls of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151469:68"/> the beſt Cinnamon-water, one quarter of a pint of red Roſe-water, one grain of Ambergreace, and twelve ſheets of Leaf-Gold; put all theſe into the Glaſs, and let it ſtand all night; then ſet it carefully into a Kettle of Water when it is cold, and faſten it very vvell about with Hay, and let the Kettle be ſet on the fire, and by degrees be made to boil; but if you ſhould put in a Pot or Glaſs into a Kettle of boiling hot Water, the ſuddain heat would break it, or elſe not.</p>
               <p>Let it ſtand thus ſlightly covered, till you find that the Sugar be quite incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated with the Juyce; when it is taken off and cold, put it up to keep, and give the Party of it two ſpoonfuls at a time, twice in a day, in the Morning and in the Afternoon, about four of the Clock.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Very fine Lozenges for a Cough of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxion of Rheum.</head>
               <p>Take two ounces of powder of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoriſh, half an ounce of powder of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeeds, one quarter of an ounce of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Elecampane, one dram of flower of Brimſtone, and one dram of prepared red Corral, one pound of double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Sugar beaten and ſearced; then with ſome Gum-Dragon ſteeped all night
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151469:69"/> in red Roſe-water, beat them into a paſte, then mold it up with a little ſearced Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and make it up into Lozenges; print them with a Seal, and dry them in the Sun, or in ſome warm place; eat of theſe often in the day or night, putting one in your mouth, and let it lye till it be quite melted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a Paſte very delicate, rich, and very pleaſant.</head>
               <p>Take one pound of red Quince-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melade, which is made very ſmooth, one ounce of candid Lemmon-pill, one ounce of candid Cittron-pill, one ounce of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Iringo-root, one ounce of candid Ginger, one ounce of Dates ſliced thin, and one ounce of Prunels; let all theſe be cut ſmall, and beaten with a little Sack to a Paſte; then put your Marmelade to them, with four ounces of ſweet Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds blanched and beaten, and four ounces of fine Sugar beaten and ſearced, and a little Gum-Dragon, ſteeped all night in fair water, when you have beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them extream well, then take it out and mold it up with ſearced Sugar, and make it into little Cakes, of what form you pleaſe, and dry them upon Wafer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheets
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151469:69"/> on Tin-plates in an Oven after Bread is drawn. If you pleaſe you may perfume ſome of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make good Drink to comfort you in a cold Morning.</head>
               <p>Take a pint and a half of Claret-Wine, and half a pint of ſtale ſtrong-Beer; boil them with ſuch Spice as you like very well, and a little Lemmon-pill; then take the Yolks of four or five Eggs, and beat them very well; then put ſo much Sugar into your Wine, as you think will well ſweeten it; and after mixing ſome of your hot Wine with the Eggs, brew them and the Wine ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well together, and let there be a little piece of Butter in it. Be ſure to brew it a pace that it curdle not, for then it is ſpoiled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make an excellent Cordial Electuary, for to reſtore one that is weak, or againſt Melancholy.</head>
               <p>Take of Conſerve of Burrage flowers, Roſemary flowers, of Marigold flowers, of Sage flowers, of Benorty flowers; of each of theſe one ounce, two ounces of Sirrop
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151469:70"/> of Clove-Gilly flowers, two ounces of the Sirrop of the juyce of Cittrons, one dram of Confection of Alkermes, two ounces of the beſt Cinnamon Water, and twelve or fourteen leaves of Leaf-Gold, with one ounce of prepared Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, either White or Red; mix all theſe together very well, and take about the quantity of a Walnut every night when you go to Bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very good Cordial Water without the trouble of a Still.</head>
               <p>Take two quarts of Brandy, and keep it in a great Glaſs with a reaſonable narrow mouth; put into it of Cloves, Nutmeg, Cinnamon and Ginger, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demon ſeeds, Coriander ſeeds, Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, Liquoriſh, of each of theſe half an ounce bruiſed; Long-pepper and Grains of each one dram bruiſed, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campane one quarter of an ounce brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; let all theſe ſteep in the Brandy a fortnight, then pour it out into another Glaſs ſoftly, ſo long as it will run clear; then put more Brandy into the Glaſ, where the Ingredients are, and let that ſtand three weeks; and ſo along as you
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151469:70"/> find there is any ſtrength in the Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, ſtill put in more Brandy, and let it ſtand every time longer and longer.</p>
               <p>Then take your firſt two quarts of Brandy which you poured off, and put in it four ounces of White Sugar-Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſo much Sirrop of Clove-Gilly flowers as will well colour it, with ſtore of Leaf-Gold; give two ſpoonfuls at a time: It is good in caſe of any Illneſs or Swouning, to drive out any infection and venemous humors; it is good for wind in the Stomach, and to keep out Cold.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A pretty Sweet-mèat made of Grapes, very good in Feavors.</head>
               <p>Take Grapes and pluck them from their Stalks, and bruiſe them well; then ſtrain them through a Strainer made of <hi>French</hi> Canvas; then ſet that juyce in a Gally-pot into a Kettle of boiling Water for three hours, then take the weight of it in fine Sugar, and boil it to a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy height, then put in your juyce of Grapes, and boil it till it be very clear, and ſcum it well; then put it into Glaſſes, and ſet them into a Stove for a while.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:151469:71"/>
               <head>To make Marmelade with Barberries, and Pippins.</head>
               <p>Take one pound of fine Sugar, and a pint of Water, and boil them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſcum them very well; then put into that Sirrop one pound of the beſt Pippins pared, and cut in quarters and Coared; boil them quick in this Sirrop till they are extream clear; then take them and bruiſe them as ſmall as you can with the back of a Spoon; then put to them one pound of Conſerve of Barberries that is curiouſly made, and ſtir them well together, and let them boil till they are well incorporated, and then put them into Glaſſes. This is very Cordial and pleaſant in Feavors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To Candy Fruits after they have lien in Sirrop.</head>
               <p>Take any ſort of Fruit which you have preſerved; as Apples, Pears, Plumbs, Oranges, Lemmons, Citrons, or any other, and lay them out of their Sirrop all night to drain; then lay them upon Sieves, and ſet them into a warm Oven to dry; then waſh them over with Wat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:151469:71"/> wherein Gum-Arabick hath lien to ſteep one night and do it with a Feather; then have in readineſs ſome White Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Candy, beaten not fine but groſly, and ſome ſmall, ſome bigger; ſo ſoon as you have waſhed your Fruit with Gum-water, then ſtrew it over with this Sugar Candy, ſo thick as the Gum will hold them on, and lay them upon ſlicked-Papers to dry in the Sun, and turn them often; and if you ſee any fault mend it with more Gum-water and Sugar.</p>
               <p>This is an extraordinary pretty way, and looks very delicately; and as they lie in the Sun they will ſparkle like Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds: it is ſoon done, and with as little Coſt as that which taketh up more time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a pretty Toy to hang up in the Kitchin to catch Flies, or rather to keep them from ſpoiling the Pewter, or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling People.</head>
               <p>Take a ſquare Trencher, and bore a hole at each Corner; then take four Cucumbers of an equal bigneſs, and not too long, and let them every one have ſtalks, by which you muſt tie them with
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151469:72"/> pack-thred to the four holes of the Trencher, and let your Trencher be painted over; and when it is dry waſh it over with Gum-water, and ſtrew it thick with French-froſt; then take ſome Barley, and ſtick your Cucumbers thick with the Corns, with the growing ends outward; then waſh them over with Gum-water, and Froſt them, and ſo let them dry as they hang; and on the top of the Trencher ſet ſome pretty kinds of Toys, as Babies, Dogs, Birds, or any thing you fancy better, and tie knots of fine Ribbon at every Corner, which may hide the Stalks of the Cucumbers; they do look ſtrangely and prettily, and the ſight of them is pleaſing to Children to quiet them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To lay on Leaf-Gold or Silver to any thing you would Gild.</head>
               <p>Take Gum-water, made with Arabick, and let it be pretty ſtiff; then lay it on with your Pencil where you would Gild; then take a little Cuſhion, made for the purpoſe, of very ſmooth Leather, and upon that cut your Gold with a ſharp Knife, as you will; and to take it up,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151469:72"/> draw the edge of your Knife finely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Tongue, that it may be only wet, with which, do-but touch the very edge of your Gold and it will come up, and you may lay it as you liſt; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you lay it on, let your Gum be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt dry, or elſe it will drown your Gold: and when you have laid it, preſs it down hard with the skut of a Hare, and when it is dry, burniſh it over with a Dogs-tooth. This is the right way to lay on either Gold or Silver. You may gild any Wood, or Stone, or Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meats, as what you make in Sugar, Plate, or ſuch like.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To dreſs up a Chimney very fine for the Summer time, as I have done many, and they have been liked very well.</head>
               <p>Firſt, take a pack-thred and faſten it even to the inner part of the Chimney, ſo high as that you can ſee no higher as you walk up and down the Houſe; you muſt drive in ſeveral Nails to hold this pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thred, for that is to hold up all your work; then get good ſtore of old green Moſs from Trees, and melt an equal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Bees-wax and Roſin together,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151469:73"/> and while it is hot, dip the wrong ends of the Moſs in it, and preſently clap it upon your pack-thred, and preſs it down hard with your hand; you muſt make haſt, elſe it will cool before you can faſten it, and then it will fall down; do ſo all round where the pack-thred goes, and the next row you muſt joyn to that ſo that it may ſeem all in one, thus do till you have finiſhed it down to the bottom: then take ſome other kind of Moſs, of a whitiſh-colour and ſtiff, and of ſeveral ſorts or kinds, and place that upon the other, here and there careleſly, and in ſome places put a good deal, and ſome a little; then any kind of fine Snail-ſhells, in which the Snails are dead, and little Toad-ſtools, which are very old, and look like Velvet, or any other thing that is old and pretty; place it here and there as your fancy ſerves, and faſten all with Wax and Roſin. Then for the Hearth of your Chimney, you may lay ſome Orpan-Sprigs in order all over, and it will grow as it lies; and according to the Seaſon, get what flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers you can, and ſtick in as if they grew, and a few ſprigs of Sweet-Bryer: the Flowers you muſt renew every Week<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:151469:73"/> but the Moſs will laſt all the Summer, till it will be time to make a fire; and the Orpan vvill laſt near two Months. A Chimney thus done doth grace a Room exceedingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another way for Chimneys, very fine; but will not laſt half ſo long.</head>
               <p>Take a fine thin Wainſcot-board, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three quarters of a yard long, and proportionably broad, for what you do intend it; let it be cut in what form beſt pleaſes you.</p>
               <p>I have ſeen ſome cut like a Roſe and Crown; ſome a Flower de Luce; ſome other flowers: when it is cut out, let it be all over thick with pieces of Wier ſharped at one end, and drove in about an inch in length, each of them: then lay it upon a Table, and take ſome Clay wetted a little, and lay all over it, till you have quite filled up the Wiers with the Clay, for it is they muſt hold it on: Then round about the edges every where, ſtick it thick with little ſmall ſprigs of green Tamerick or Cypreſs; or for want of either of theſe, take Ewe-ſprigs, and be ſure to ſtick them ſo
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151469:74"/> that not any part of the edges may be diſcovered; then according to the form of the Board you muſt chooſe your Flowers and Herbs.</p>
               <p>If it be for a Roſe, then your Flowers muſt be all Red, yet of divers kinds; if there be a Crown that muſt be all of Yellow flowers; if a Flower de Luce, then Blew, or Purple and Yellow, and ſo to every other: let your Flowers be all picked ready, and every ſort laid by themſelves; then run the Stalks of them into the Clay near to the Flower, and ſo do till you have finiſhed all; and put the Greens alſo in their proper place, as in the leaves and bearbs of the Flowers; when you have quite done, ſet it into the Chimney, and let the bottom of it reſt within a great Flower-pot, ſuch as they make for Chimneys: It muſt be lifted by three or four People at once very carefully, or elſe you will ſpoil all; for it will be ſo weighty, and the Board ſo thin, that it is eaſily broke in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. When you have ſet it as it ſhould be, then cover your Chimneys-Hearth with Green things, and then with fine Flowers, and be ſure to cover your Pot alſo that there may be no diſcovery; it
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151469:74"/> will be freſh two Months if you ſprinkle it with Water.</p>
               <p>I have here directed you to many things, which will (no doubt) be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and profitable to you. Give me leave now to treat a little concerning the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of the Female Sex, and to give Counſel to thoſe who need it, becauſe I find there is ſome need of it. In my Book called <hi>The Ladies Guide,</hi> I did ſpeak very much to them, but moſt to the Younger ſort. My intention was to have inlarged that Book, if Mr. <hi>Newman</hi> had done me that right, as to have let me known when he vvould print it; but it was his pleaſure to employ another; who hath ſo transformed the Book, that it is nothing like what I had written: It is now about Eight years or more ſince I writ that <hi>Guide,</hi> which was ſold for twelve pence the Book; and it is above twelve Months ſince the New one came out, which ſold for half a Crown the Book. I thought to have ſued him for it, but he very cunningly prevented that by taking advantage of me; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he muſt give me leave to ſay the truth, That that Edition was none of my Writing, I will never diſown
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151469:75"/> what I do Write, nor am I willing to own what I writ not. He did indeed (after I had Cavilled with him, and ſhewed him vvherein I vvas abuſed by his Writer) give me a ſmall matter to look it over, and told me that I ſhould take out, and put in the room of it vvhat I beſt pleaſed, and agreed with me by the Sheet vvhat to give me, which I did accordingly: and truly, I dealt very Friendly with him; for I took away nothing but that which was ſcandalous, ridiculous, and impertinent, and put in only that vvhich vvas inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and harmleſs: So willing was I to be peaceable vvith him, and I thought he vvould have been Civil to me; but vvhen I brought it to him, he did not give me the one half of what I bargain'd for: I asking him why he dealt ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily with me? He ſaid, it was his humour to give me no more. So now he may take notice that it is my Humour to let all People know, that I was abuſed in that his late printed Book. He told me, he cared not for my Name, he would print it without it: if he do ſo, I have nothing to do with it. I ſhould not ſpeak ſo much did I not find a prejudice:
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151469:75"/> for People of vvorth do wonder why I would Write ſo; and I have vindicated my ſelf to thoſe who told me of it, with telling the Truth. Now to proceed:</p>
               <p>In that Book which was mine (called <hi>The Ladies Guide)</hi> there was as good Inſtructions to Youth, as I can imagine to give; and alſo to all manner of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, what their duty was each one in their ſeveral Employs; and there vvas the Miſtreſſes part as well as theirs: The Wife to the Husband, the Widow to the World: and indeed when I writ it, I could not tell how to ſay more. He would do himſelf much right, as well as me, to print the ſame <hi>Verbatim:</hi> in the mean time I deſire you to obſerve vvhat I ſhall ſay, which may do ſome of you much good for the future. There are very many at this preſent time vvho vvant Services, both Gentlewomen and others, and ſome of them very well accompliſht (thoſe I find to be the moſt humble, and willing to pleaſe:) Another ſort there be which have little in them; yet none but great Places vvill ſerve them; vvhich vvhen they have wearied themſelves to find, and at laſt miſs of what they have propounded to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151469:76"/> they are ready to run any extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Courſe ſtill to purchaſe fine Cloaths, then to conform to any Civility or Manners, or to take the Advice of thoſe who would aſſiſt them. Some who have apt Wits, and that dame Nature hath been favourable to, they are Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be Players: Some other of them to Bawdy-Houſes: Some are tempted to Steal. And thus many Wickedneſſes are committed againſt God and Man, and themſelves brought into a moſt miſerable condition of living, or to a ſhameful end: whilſt the firſt I ſpake of are diligent to get wherewith to feed and cloath them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by ſome honeſt employ or other, till ſuch time as it ſhall pleaſe God better to provide for them, and keep cloſe to their buſineſs (not ſhewing themſelves in the Streets, but vvhen they have juſt occaſion to go forth:) Such as theſe laſt ſhall never want my aſſiſtance, if it lye in my power to help them; for it is a great deal of pity but that all Ingenious and Honeſt minded Perſons ſhould be encouraged. I do love ſuch vvith my heart, and do beſeech them ſtill to truſt in him vvho is able to remedy all, or to give patience in ſufferings. I will now
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151469:76"/> tell you ſeveral<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Cauſes vvhich may bring good Children, and Children of good Parents, many times, to be in Diſtreſs; as alſo, Why the other do commonly run into Wickedneſs, and vvhat may for the future prevent ſuch Miſcarriages; vvith my loving and Chriſtian Advice to both their Parents and them; and ſomewhat to thoſe under whoſe Tuition they are, or may happen under.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Cauſe why good Children, or the Children of worthy Parents, are oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in a diſtreſſed Condition.</head>
               <p>IT hapneth oft-times, that a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man having a good Eſtate, but many Children, he, and the care of a good Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together doth make a very good ſhift to bring them all up (in appearance to the eye of the World) very handſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; their Attire being ſuch as becomes his and her Children; their Education ſuch as is fitting for, or the beſt vvhich can be attained in that
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:151469:77"/> place they live in: this they do till ſome of the Eldeſt are Women grown; and by that time they are conſidering how to beſtow them in the World, finding the Charge to be too great for them. If an Elder one Marry; although there be one leſs in the Family, yet carries more with her, than, if ſhe had ſtayed, would have been ſpent upon her: Her Husband perhaps in a ſhort time, by playing the Ill-fellow, is quite ruin'd, and his Wife turn'd home to her Parents again, with a Child or two to provide for. Where, after a vvhile, ſhe cannot abide to hear her Husband blamed, neither is ſhe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to burden her Parents ſo much; ſhe endeavours to get into ſome good Service, to be Nurſe, and leaves her Child or Children vvith them. She hath her affliction, and doth vvaſte her ſelf vvith grief and ſorrow. The Parents find themſelves ſo burden'd, that they muſt needs ſend ſome of the reſt out to Service: and here they come to <hi>London,</hi> perhaps to ſome Cozin, or ſome Friend, thinking to get ſome place or other quickly, but find it a hard buſineſs. Their Friends beginning to grumble at their being; their Cloaths beginning to wear
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151469:77"/> out, and all their Mony ſpent; then do they find themſelves in a deſperate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and do ſeek ſome place or other to Lodge in, and are content to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in any honeſt way to get a penny, till they can procure a Service; being not vvilling to return to their Parents, to add to their grief. Some men are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done by Surety-ſhip; ſome with the Ill-chance of a Die; ſome by Fire; ſome by Sea; ſome by long-ſickneſs; ſome by Robbery; ſome by Suits in Law; ſome by War; and many other waies there are to bring Men to deſtruction; and then their Wives and Children muſt needs be expoſed to Miſery: The poor Mother, ſhe employs her ſelf in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what or other to maintain her ſelf, and the younger Children, who are not yet able to take care of themſelves: and for the Elder ones, they are forced to Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and are fain to accept for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, which are but ſlaviſh, rather then to follow any Ill-courſe of Life. All theſe, you will ſay, have their Afflictions; and you have ſufficient Reaſons for the Cauſes thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:151469:78"/>
               <head>The Cauſes why others do commonly run into Miſchief and Wickedneſs.</head>
               <p>They are ſuch whoſe Fathers have died vvhen they vvere young, and their Mother perhaps by a ſecond match hath ruin'd her ſelf, and them; or ſhe hath been left in ſo miſerable a condition, that ſhe hath not been capable of Adviſing them, nor able to bring them up as ſhe ſhould do in the Fear of God: ſo that wanting that, they have grown Refra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to her, and forgot their Duty, and then liable to all Temptations whatever. Some Parents have both died, and left their Children to the Care of ſome near Friend, and their Eſtates to be managed by them for the Childrens good; and thoſe Truſtees have been neglectful of thoſe in their Charge, and have ſpent all which vvas left for them, and then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them to the mercy of the World, vvithout Education or Mony: And ſome are naturally inclin'd to Wickedneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that is worſt of all; For it is as hard to bring them to good, as to vvaſh a Black-Moor white, or to make a Foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vviſe; both vvhich are I think impoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible:
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151469:78"/> ſome for vvant of good Principles, and vvhich have been left too much to their own Will, to do even vvhat they liſt, and vvhen they liſt. God knows our Nature of it ſelf is prone to nothing but Evil; therefore how happy are they that have careful Parents, that are not over-fond to leave them to their own Will, nor cruel to them in their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections; but do vviſely and ſoberly, religiouſly and lovingly Nurture them, and ſtrictly keep them to Church, and Family Duties, ſuch do ſeldome go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray; for God vvill certainly bleſs thoſe Children for the Parents ſake.</p>
               <p>And how unhappy are thoſe vvhoſe Parents are careleſs of their Childrens Education, and not only ſo, but do alſo ruine them by giving an ill Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>Of all theſe vvhich I have mentioned, I at this preſent know ſome, both Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Children, every one of their Conditions in particular, and am truly ſorry for their Affliction; for certainly there is no greater Grief than ill Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and ill Wives, cauſe to one another, or vvhat ill Children create to their Parents or they to them.
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:151469:79"/> I thank God, though I have paſſed through many more Afflictions and Troubles then thouſands of my Sex, yet I never had an ill Husband, nor undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Children; but (on the contrary) I have been marryed to two Worthy, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, and brave Perſons; and I have four Sons, as good Children as ever Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did bear. For my own part, I can ſay nothing for my ſelf, what Wife or Mother I have been; but if no Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion come againſt me, I have no reaſon to accuſe my ſelf. I give thanks and glory to Almighty God, for what bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits I have received from time to time; eſpecially for thoſe Bleſſings which I do at this preſent enjoy; The lives and welfare of my Dear Children, The happy choice which two of them have made in their Wives, and that I have lived to ſee two ſweet Babes from their Loyns. Such like comfort as this I wiſh to all good Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:151469:79"/>
               <head>Advice to Parents concerning their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and advice to Children concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Parents: Alſo to any Perſon under whoſe Tuition they may be; which (if well obſerved) may prevent much wickedneſs for the future.</head>
               <p>YOU who are the Mothers of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, I advice you to have an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Care, firſt, That they be well-grounded in the Principles of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: That they keep duly to Church and to Family Duties: That they duly ask you Bleſſing; and make them to know their Diſtance, by keeping them to all due Reverence: Let them be lovingly and quietly Governed; not with perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Chiding and Brawling, but treat with them mildly and gently; unleſs you find them Refractory to your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; if ſo, then ſome Auſtere lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage muſt be uſed: and when they do well, be kind to them, and encourage them. Let them not be too nice in their Diet; but teach them to know, that
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:151469:80"/> God is worthy of Thanks and Praiſe for the leaſt bit or drop they Eat or Drink. Let them be neat and decent in their Habit, not at all Extravagant: have a care what Company they keep, and do not give them too much Liberty, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deny them lawful Recreations. Let them not have the command of your Purſe, neither let them be without a little; and as they manage that, give them more. Let them learn whatever they are capable of, or that you have opportunity for the Learning, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially what their Genious is inclined to; for that to be ſure they will be excellent at. Let them be fully employed, but with diverſity of things; that will be a delight to them, and they will have no time to give heed to wicked Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor no room for idle Thoughts. Suffer them not to tell you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Lie, but encourage them alwaies to tell the Truth; for lying is the ground of all Miſchief. Teach them to be Houſwifely in their Cloaths, and too ſparing of them. Let them learn the way of Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping, by acting your Commands. Let them know how to entertain Friends, and to be Courteous to Strangers, and
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:151469:80"/> loving to your Servants; not Dominee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring over them, nor yet too familiar with them. Adviſe them to be modeſt in their Carriage in mens Company, for fear of ill Cenſures. Suffer them not to be too loud in their Diſcourſe, nor Snappiſh and Peeviſh with any. Give them Counſel, who are your Children, to Love one another, and alwaies to give more than ordinary Reſpect to the Eldeſt.</p>
               <p>Theſe things, if you will pleaſe to obſerve<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to Command them, and they will be careful to obey you, you ſhall not need to doubt of your happineſs in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and they will alwaies have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to bleſs God for ſuch a Parent, or Parents, who were not only the Cauſe of their being, but alſo of their well-being. But if by ill-Fate (after all this Care) you ſhould have a Rebellious and refractory Child, your frequent Prayers to Almighty God will be the only way to reclaim them. But truly, I do think there is no other way, nor no better way to prevent Wickedneſs in Children, then this I have propoſed; which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, you may ſay is needleſs, becauſe you know already how to order them.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:151469:81"/> I beſeech your pardon; for we are not ſo ſit to adviſe our ſelves as others, for our Indulgence oftentimes blinds us: Therefore we are fitter to Adviſe one another, then any one to Adviſe their ſelves.</p>
               <p>Neglect of Childrens good, by being over-Fond ruines them. Too much Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity doth ſo too: I cannot tell which is worſt: Therefore it is good to ſhun both, and to keep the middle way.</p>
               <p>All you Children, who have Parents living, obſerve your Duty to them, and whatſoever they Command you, do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and God will bleſs you the better; for he hath Commanded you, to <hi>Honour your Father and Mother.</hi> If they do Chide you, bear it patiently, and do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them to continue their Anger by unreverent Anſwers, but be ſilent and ſubmiſſive to them.</p>
               <p>Be careful of your time when you Learn any thing, and do not let the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (which they are willing to disburſe for you) be loſt through your Idleneſs. Obſerve every one how they do order their Houſes, and how they do make this or that; and what you cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:151469:81"/> that write down, that it may ſtead you another time.</p>
               <p>Be careful of your Parents when they are Sick, and reverence them when they are Aged. Burthen them not when you come to be of Age of Diſcretion, but think with your ſelf how, or which way to caſe them.</p>
               <p>Take heed what Company you keep, for fear they corrupt you, and draw you into miſchief.</p>
               <p>Go not from your Parents without their leave, leaſt you grieve them; and bring a Curſe upon your ſelves, by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeying them.</p>
               <p>Depend on no Friends, but truſt in him who is able always to provide for you, and that will never fail thoſe who wait upon him patiently without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt; he is never weary of hearing the complaint of the Widow and Fatherleſs, nor of any who are in Diſtreſs. On the other ſide, do not neglect or ſlight your Friends; but ſhew your duty to them in your reſpects, and give ear to their good Counſel.</p>
               <p>When you are abſent from your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, be ſure to Write to them ſo often as need ſhall require, and let not what
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:151469:82"/> you Write be impertinent and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
               <p>If God hath bleſt you with a good Lady or Miſtreſs, be you obſerving al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies what may pleaſe her, and be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and modeſt in your Behaviour; be neat and Houſwifely in your Cloaths, and lay up what Mony can handſomly be ſpared. Be careful of what ſhe gives you, or what you have in your Charge, that by ſo doing you may oblige her to be loving and kind to you, and cauſe her to ſpeak well of you. Do not keep familiarity with any, but thoſe by whom you may improve your time.</p>
               <p>If you be an Apprentice; be careful that you learn your Trade well, that you may live another day: and let not the Mony your Parent or Friends gave for your good be thrown away by your Neglect and Careleſneſs.</p>
               <p>If God hath bleſt you with a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, be careful to improve it, and truſt not too much upon it. Never conſent to Marry with any man without your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents or Friends Conſent, leaſt you be the Cauſe of their Grief and Sorrow; and bring your ſelf to Affliction and Miſery.</p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:151469:82"/>
               <p> All you who have any Young Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, or Gentlewomen, under your Charge or Tuition, be you alwaies mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of their Good as well as your own. If they are put to School to you, or Apprentices, let them not loſe their Youthful time, which cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed; but keep them ſtrictly to their Duty in a loving and mild way. If they come as Servants to you for Wages, be not cruel to them in ſevere Language; nor impoſe more upon them than they ſhall be able to perform; nor pinch them in their Diet, but allow them ſuch Food as is convenient for them. When they do their Duty to you, be you pleaſed to encourage them, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them good words, and beſtow ſome ſmall Favour on them. Adviſe them how to lay out their Mony, and never to ſpend all, but keep ſome for a reſerve. Let them go decently, not vainly and proudly: and command them duly to the Service of God.</p>
               <p>I think I have ſpoken ſufficiently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o all I mentioned; and as I mean well, ſo, I hope, you will all of you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake it well. With this my advice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vviſh you the Bleſſing of GOD,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:151469:83"/> and do deſire the ſame from you upon my ſelf; which is all the Gratification I do deſire or expect from you.</p>
               <p>Be pleaſed to take notice, that in my Book <hi>The Ladies Guide,</hi> I did give di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for the Writing of Letters; but it was only to ſuch as were Young, and to Servants. I think it not amiſs to give ſome Forms or Patterns of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for Elder, and more-ſerious people: for I do daily find, that in Writing moſt Women are to ſeek. They many times ſpend their time in Learning a good Hand; but their Engliſh and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is, The one not eaſie to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, The other weak and impertinent. I meet with Letters my ſelf ſometimes, that I could even tear them as I read them, they are ſo full of impertinency, and ſo tedious. I will begin with one of them; not that you ſhould take example by it to do the ſame; but I ſet it as a thing to be abhorr'd, and ſhun'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:151469:83"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Siſter to a Brother, far diſtant from her.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Brother,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>MY love remembred unto you, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that you are in good health as I am at the writing hereof, praiſed be God. I hope you got well to your Journeys end; I pray let us know. My Father and my Mother do remember their Love to you; and my Siſter <hi>Betty</hi> remembers her Love to you; and my Brother <hi>John,</hi> and my Brother <hi>Nicholas</hi> do ſo too: and my Couzin <hi>Jane</hi> is Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and ſhe doth remember her Love to you, and her Husband remembers his Love to you, and ſays, he would be glad to ſee you, and to be acquainted with you. My Couzin <hi>Robin</hi> remembers his Love to you; and my Couzin <hi>Nan</hi> remembers her Love to you; and I remember my Love to you. So I reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your loving Siſter till death,</hi> Elizabeth Spanner.</signed> You ſee in this Letter how ridiculous it is to Write after this manner, the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage being both impertinent and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: Give me leave now to ſhew you
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:151469:84"/> what ill Engliſh is, and tell me which is worſt, for I do not yet know.</closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Daughter to her Mother.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Mother,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>MY duty remembred unto you hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that you are in good helth as i am at the Riting hereof praſed be God, this is to let you underſtand that i have receved the things you ſent to me by <hi>Tomas Frenge</hi> and he had a grot of me for the bringing them, i pray do not forget my Come I left in the Kichen windo and my Aporn in the Chamber, pray ſend them al to me, i hop my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is wel and my brother <hi>Ned</hi> and my ſuſter <hi>Joice</hi> and i hop godie <hi>welſh</hi> is wel, thus with my love and duty to you i reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>your dutiful daſter</hi> Ann Blackwell.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Now I have ſhewed you how ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous and ſimple, and how impertinent theſe are; I will alſo ſhew you how to Write that it may be effectual in what
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:151469:84"/> you ſhall deſire, and alſo acceptable to thoſe you Write to. You ſhall find here Letters upon all Occaſions which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly concern us; and ſome others which accidentally may happen. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that you are not to Write word for word, but to take the manner of the Form it will teach you, and by ſo doing you may ſave your Purſe, and keep your Secrets to your ſelf. Take notice that thoſe Letters I ſhall write as from People well knowing, is not to teach them how to Write, but to teach you how to Anſwer them.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Mother to a Daughter in a Ladies Service.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Child,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Do deſire to know how you do in your Service, and whether or no you think you ſhall be able to perform what you have undertaken: however I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you to be very diligent to pleaſe, that you may by that oblige your Lady to be kind to you, and willing to keep you. Be careful to ſerve God, and be pleaſing in your Carriage to all People. So ſoon as I know you ſhall ſtay I will ſend your Trunck, and other things.
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:151469:85"/> Thus with your Fathers and my Bleſſing to you, and your Brothers and Siſters Love, I reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your careful and loving Mother,</hi> Sarah Wild.</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>March</hi> 3. 1663.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Anſwer.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Moſt Dear and Honoured Mother,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Received yours dated <hi>March</hi> the third, and do give you humble thanks for your Motherly Care of me; I have not yet been long enough to give you a full account how my Lady will like me: I hope well, becauſe as yet ſhe finds little or no fault with me. I beſeech you to aſſure your ſelf, that if I ſhould be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned home to you again, it ſhall be for what I cannot do, not what I will not do; but I hope better things, and I will ſtay here if it be poſſible, for it is a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Family, and they are very kind to me. My Lady likes my Dreſſing very well, and alſo what I Starch; but ſhe would fain have me more curious in my Point-Work. She will not let me waſh her Chamber becauſe I ſhould not ſpoil my Hands for Work. If ſhe like me well, I
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:151469:85"/> ſhall be glad, for I like her Service very well. Thus with my humble Duty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to you and to my Father; with my Love to my Brothers and Siſters, and to all my Friends: I take my leave, and do beſeech you to eſteem me as I endeavour to be,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Dear Mother,</salute>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your moſt Obedient Daughter,</hi> Mary Wild</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>March</hi> 10. 1663.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Siſter to a Brother.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Brother,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>YOur abſence at firſt cauſed much Grief, both to our Parents, and to us your loving Brothers and Siſters; but ſince we hear of your welfare, and very good liking, we are as much joyed, and do heartily wiſh and pray for the continuance of the ſame. We want the comfort of your Company; but we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live by ſight of each other. This is a miſerable World, and every one muſt be Careful and Induſtrious, or elſe it is impoſſible to wade the Troubles which it brings people in. We are happy in our Parents, that they took ſuch good Care
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:151469:86"/> for us in our Education, to make us able to live in the World. I thank God I am in a very good Place, where I have the Love and good word of the People I ſerve: I do not doubt but to gain it more and more. My Mother as well as my Father. Commanded me to write to you, and to let you know their Indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, or elſe my Father would have Written to you himſelf. He hath been ill of the Gout, and my Mother of an Ague; but I hope they will both do very well again. My Brother <hi>James</hi> hath alſo hurt his Side by a Fall, but he is on the mending hand. Thus with my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Mothers. Bleſſing to you; with mine, my Brothers and Siſters Love to you, I reſt,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Dear Brother,</salute>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your ever affectionate Siſter,</hi> Martha Hopewell.</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Decemb.</hi> 4. 1665.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From one Friend to another.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Honoured Friend,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Have written to you ſeveral times, to let you know what I have done concerning the Buſineſs you were pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to intruſt me withal; but hearing no
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:151469:86" rendition="simple:additions"/> Anſwer, I fear my Letters have miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried. This is now again to give you an account of what I have done. So ſoon as your Letter of commands came to my Hands, I went ſtreight to Mr. <hi>Shewer,</hi> and demanded your Mony, delivering the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Attorney you ſent, to peruſe, that he might know the truth; but he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to while-off, told me, that he would pay it to you ſo ſoon as he could ſee you, and ſpeak with you about ſome Buſineſs which concerns your good. If he keep his Word it will do very well. I was alſo with Mrs. <hi>Madewell,</hi> and ſhe hath paid me; alſo with Mr. <hi>Stockwell,</hi> and he hath alſo paid me. I pray do me the favour as to ſee my little Girl for me, and know what Nurſe wants, and I will ſend it down. I ſhall trouble you no more at this preſent, ſave only with the Service and Reſpects of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your moſt affectionate Kinſwoman, and humble Servant,</hi> Ann Boarman.</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Novemb.</hi> 2. 1667.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="156" facs="tcp:151469:87"/>
                     <head>The Anſwer.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Received yours; wherein you have given me full ſatisfaction concerning what I deſired you, for which I moſt humbly thank you, and do deſire you will be pleaſed to accept this Token from me: I wiſh it were better; but I know your Temper ſo well, that your Eye will not be over-curious with me, nor mind the Gift more than the Giver, but take all in good part. I have ſeen your little one, which is in good health. Nurſe wants nothing as yet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> All our Friends here are well, and deſire you to accept their Love and Service. Thus with mine in particular to you, I reſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your ever obliged Friend, and devoted Servant, <hi>J. M.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Novemb.</hi> 2. 1667.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From one Siſter to another.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Siſter,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Am very glad to hear you do ſo well, and that you have recovered your Health again; I pray God continue it to you. My Mother remembers her
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:151469:87"/> Love and Bleſſing to you, and deſires you will ſend her the Receipt for the Stone; for ſhe hath great need of it, both for her ſelf and others. She deſires to know when you think you ſhall come to Town. I am in a little haſte, and nought elſe at preſent, but my dear Love and Reſpects to you, and to tell you that I am, and ever will be,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Dear Siſter,</salute>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Yours ever to love and ſerve you,</hi> Mary South.</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Decemb.</hi> 6. 1664.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Lady to a Gentlewoman, whom ſhe hath a kindneſs for.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My dear Friend,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>YOur Humility commands what Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour lies in my power to do for you or yours; therefore if you can conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend that your Daughter ſhall be a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to me, you ſhall find that I will be more a Mother than a Miſtreſs to her. I doubt not of her Abilities, ſince I know your care hath been very much for her Education. However, I may find her not at preſent altogether fit for my Service, yet I am confident ſhe will be capable that I do intend her good;
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:151469:88" rendition="simple:additions"/> and in relation to that, I know ſhe will endeavour to pleaſe me, or elſe ſhe muſt not be your Daughter. Fear nothing in me, I value your worth, and ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo value your Child; and what is wanting in her, I ſhall not ſpare my Purſe to give a full Accompliſhment to her; therefore if you pleaſe to ſend her ſpeedily it will be very well, becauſe at this time I am deſtitute; yet I might have the Choice of many Accompliſht Women, were it not a particular Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I have to you, that cauſes me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe them. I deſire you will let her be handſomly Cloathed for your Credits ſake; which, if you lack Mony to do it, let me know, and I will ſoon furniſh you. Thus deſiring you not to delay, I remain</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Friend to love and ſerve you, <hi>M. C.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:151469:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>The Anſwer.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Madam,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>YOu have ſo much obliged me by your goodneſs and Charity towards me and my poor Child, that we are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven tranſported with joy. Poor Girl, ſhe ſleeps not in the night, leaſt any thing ſhould happen to hinder her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to you. Her Cloaths are making, but indeed I have not wherewith to pay for them, nor to provide other things which ſhe very much wants: therefore ſince it is your Ladyſhips plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſend me Mony, I beſeech you it may be ſpeedily; and ſo ſoon as her Cloaths are finiſhed, and other things bought, ſhe ſhall tender her Duty and Service to you, and I will give her the beſt Inſtructions I can. I hope ſhe will not be refractory to her Duty, but ſtrive to be a good and faithful Servant; yet, if ſhe ſhould have any Childiſh faults, I beſeech you, be pleaſed to let me know, that I may rebuke her for them. Be pleaſed to accept of my humble Service, and to believe that I am,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Madam,</salute>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>The moſt humble of your poor Servants,</hi> C. H.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="160" facs="tcp:151469:89"/>
                     <head>From a Wife to her Husband, Craving his pardon for her long abſence from him.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Heart,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WHen you gave me leave for my Journey, I did intend no other but to Return according to your Order; but the much Kindneſs, and Intreaty for my ſtay, together with the late very ill Weather, hath cauſed me to tranſgreſs my bounds; which I do wholly truſt to your Goodneſs to pardon, and do the more hope for it, becauſe it is the firſt time I ever offended you in this Nature. I do deſire, you will pleaſe to let me know how you and my Children do, and whether our Servant doth her Duty; likewiſe how our little one at Nurſe doth: And I deſire you alſo to ſend me ſome Mony ſpeedily, to bear my Charges to you. This is all at preſent, ſave only the Love and Duty of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt obedient, and loving Wife, <hi>E. D.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:151469:89"/>
                     <head>From an Aunt to her Neece.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Neece;</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>YOur Parents being Dead, I would have you take notice that I ſhall take Care of you; therefore do not think your ſelf deſtitute in the World. On the other ſide, I would have you endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour what you can for your ſelf, in an honeſt way; but want nothing that is fitting for you. Let me know at any time what you would have, and I ſhall furniſh you; either with Mony, or with Neceſſaries. Be careful you do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to Marry with any Man, without my leave, for fear you make your ſelf Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy. I have ſent you a Bible, and twenty ſhillings in Mony by the Carryer. I pray let me know if you have received it or no. Be careful in the firſt place to ſerve God, and to pleaſe thoſe whom you ſerve; and you ſhall never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt Affectionate Aunt, <hi>M. C.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="162" facs="tcp:151469:90"/>
                     <head>The Anſwer.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Honoured Aunt,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Never doubted of your Kindneſs; but could not have expected ſo much as you are pleaſed to ſhew me, becauſe I know I have never deſerved it: But ſince I know your Care for me, I do aſſure you that it ſhall cauſe me to be more careful of my ſelf. I have received the Mony and the Bible, and do give you moſt humble and hearty Thanks for them. My Lady finds little or no fault with me, therefore I preſume I do pleaſe her. I have not an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock of Cloaths, neither can I complain of much want; yet if I had a new and faſhionable Gown it would do me Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. I have ſomewhat towards it, and if you pleaſe to make it up, I ſhall be the more bound to pray for you; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no Body is now eſteemed without fine Cloaths. For my Marrying with any one without your Conſent, I ſhall not be ſo mad; neither do I think any man will as yet be troubled with me. When you think it is time, I had rather take your Choice than my own: In the mean time, I ſhall endeavour only to perform
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:151469:90"/> what I am obliged to; and to ſhew my Duty to you. Thus with the tender of my humbleſt Reſpects, and Service, I take leave humbly, and remain,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Dear Aunt,</salute>
                        <signed>Your moſt obliged Niece, and moſt humble Servant. <hi>E. C.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Widow to her Friend, deſiring her Aſſiſtance.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Stile you as I have alwaies found you: But now is the only trial of a Friend in this my neceſſity. It is not unknown to you the Charge which I have now upon me, and the many Troubles I am involved in; my Husband having had a long time of Sickneſs, and died in Debt; ſo that I have little or no Comfort in my life: Yet, if I had a Stock to begin, I could ſet up my own Trade, and live very well; but who to ask, beſides your ſelf I do not know, and how to ask you I cannot tell, having already been ſo much obliged to you; yet my Neceſſity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forces me to crave this one Favour from you, That you will pleaſe to lend to me 10 <hi>l.</hi> for the ſpace of one whole year,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:151469:91"/> and I will faithfully return it again with many Thanks. This if you will pleaſe to do, will give a new Life to</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt faithful Friend, to love and ſerve you.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Anſwer.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Am very ſorry for the occaſion of your ſad Letter, and ſhall not deny your Requeſt, in hopes that the grant thereof may make you happy: yet I do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, that were it any one elſe who did ſue to me upon ſuch an account I would deny them; for the World is ſo baſe, and Mony ſo hard to come by, that there is hardly any that will let Mony go out of their hands. I ſhall freely lend you ſo much, and for a longer time than you do propound; but I would ſain ſpeak with you firſt, and adviſe you in your Way: Therefore do not delay the time, but come as ſoon as poſſible you can, and you ſhall find me then, and for ever,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt faithful Friend, and ready to ſerve you.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:151469:91"/>
                     <head>From a Woman in Priſon to her Friend, to help her.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Suppoſe you have heard how wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully I have been dealt with ſince my Husbands departure; how they have accuſed me of what I was never guilty of, and caſt me in Priſon to my great Diſcredit, Charge and Detriment in the World. I do deſire that loving favour of you as to come and ſee me, and to lend me a ſmall ſum towards the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraying of my Charges here, and then I make no doubt but I ſhall get quickly quit of this place. <hi>Dear Friend,</hi> Have pity on me, and if it ever lie in my power, I will reſtore you Seven-fold. Thus with my due Reſpects to you, deſiring ſpeedily to hear from you, I reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your true Friend and Servant.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Anſwer.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Am extream ſorry for your Trouble, and do verily believe that you are much wronged, therefore I ſhall aſſiſt you in what I can. I have ſome buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to diſpatch this Week of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:151469:92"/> which will keep me in; but upon Monday next (God willing) I do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be with you, and anſwer your deſires: In the mean time I deſire you to comfort your ſelf, and to be aſſured that I am</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your loving Friend to ſerve you.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Seamans Wife to her Husband.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Husband,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>SInce your departure our little Boy is dead of the Small-Pox; and our Girl hath been ill too, but now I thank God ſhe is reaſonable well again. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you will remember to bring me home ſome fine things for my Houſe. <hi>Edward Long</hi> alſo deſires that you will not forget what he ſpake to you for; as alſo Mrs. <hi>Chappel.</hi> We are very glad for your ſafe Arrival, and wiſh you a ſpeedy and ſafe return; but eſpecially</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your poor, but loving Wife.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Servant to her Miſtriſs, concerning her Charge.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Madam,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>YOur ſweet Children, I thank God, are all very well, but think long for your coming<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>home. I have ſpoken with your Tenant, Goodman <hi>Porter,</hi> and
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:151469:92"/> he deſires you ſhould know that the Mony ſhall be ready for you at your Return; but as for the Widow <hi>Totnham,</hi> ſhe hath had a great Loſs lately, therefore ſhe deſires your Patience yet a while. I have no more at this time but the tender of my Duty and Service, beſeeching you to believe that I am</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your obedient Servant.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Letter of Complement from one Friend to another.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Honoured Friend,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THe laſt time I ſaw you, you laid on me ſuch an obligation of Kindneſs as I fear I ſhall never be able to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite; but I will endeavor what poſſible I can. I wiſh you would do me the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour as to lay your Commands on me, then I ſhould give you ſome proof of my Gratitude, and I know you are ſo good as that you will accept the Will for the Deed. I deſire you will pleaſe, when you have a leiſure time, to Honour me with your Company; of which I ſhall be proud as well as happy, and I preſume our Air would do no harm, but rather good; you alſo add to the Favour, if you pleaſe to let me know a little before,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:151469:93"/> that I may meet you ſome part of the way. Your God-ſon is very well, but is not able as yet to ſhew his Duty to you. I deſire you will pleaſe to bring little Miſs with you, and then I ſhall hope to enjoy your Company the longer; for I know you cannot be without her many daies. If you pleaſe to grant this, you will oblige her who is, and ever will be</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt humble Servant.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Ladies Anſwer.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Madam,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>ALL that I have ever done, and can imagine to do, cannot merit the leaſt of your expreſſions; which if I did not believe to be Realities, I ſhould wrong you much, for I am very well acquainted with your temper. For your deſire of my coming to wait on you, I do aſſure you, you might have ſpared your Invitation, for I did intend to come however; and ſeeing it is your deſire that Miſs ſhould come too, ſhe ſhall wait on you with me. I cannot tell what day I ſhall come as yet; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther am I willing to tell you if I could<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe your free and noble heart will
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:151469:93"/> be apt to tranſgreſs the bounds of my deſires; elſe I ſhould be very glad you ſhould be ſatisfied when I would come: Sometime within this fortnight I ſhall not fail you; in the mean time theſe are to let you know that I am, and ever will be</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your truly devoted, and humble Servant.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Letter from a Mother to a Daughter, who had gone aſtray from her.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Suſanna,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Could never have believed I had had ſo wicked a Child, as you have proved your ſelf in your late Actions: You have not only afflicted me, but ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ruin'd your ſelf, your Perſon and your Credit for ever. Had your Dear <hi>Father</hi> lived, you never durſt have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to think upon ſuch Wickedneſs: His Severity kept you in awe, but my Indulgence hath ſpoiled you. What Cauſe had you juſtly to leave me? I cannot tell, nor imagine any; but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that bad Company (which I have often gave you warning of) I believe hath enticed you. You are my Child ſtill, though never ſo bad, and I your Mother,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:151469:94"/> and if I thought you would be reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I would freely forgive you all that is paſt, for my heart ſtill yearns upon you; but if you reſolve to go on in Wickedneſs, think not of coming near me. Therefore bethink your ſelf ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and let me know what you intend to do. I am yet</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your very loving, though very much afflicted Mother, <hi>E. H.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Daughters Anſwer to her Mother.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear, and Honoured Mother,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>GOD forbid that your Indulgence to me ſhould be the Cauſe of my Miſcarriage. I do confeſs my Fault, and moſt humbly crave your pardon; which I deſire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I may be aſſured of before I do return to you, elſe I know not with what face I ſhall look upon you. You are not at all deceived: It was that ill Company you warned me from, which did entice me upon pretence of going only to make Merry; but after I was gone from you, I ſoon perceived they
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:151469:94"/> would have quite ruin'd me; and I fear you do believe they have in part done ſo; but I do aſſure you, that no harm hath hapned to me, ſave your juſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure for my coming away, and the diſcredit I have gotten by ſo doing. I ſtaied not in their Company, after I found. out their deſign, but gat me from them unawares, and would willingly have returned home, if I durſt: Therefore be pleaſed to quiet your Thoughts, and do not think your Child is a Strumpet, although ſhe hath done fooliſhly. If you pleaſe to receive me again, and freely to pardon me, you ſhall find that I will ſtrive alwaies to ſhun the occaſion of Evil, and ever be truly careful to obey you in all things. Therefore, <hi>Dear Mother,</hi> forgive your poor unworthy Child, and ſhe will be alwaies bound to pray for you, and ever be</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your obedient Daughter. <hi>M. H.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="172" facs="tcp:151469:95"/>
                     <head>A Letter from a Gentleman to a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his, wherein he doth advertiſe her of ſome Accuſations laid againſt her.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Madam,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Chanced not long ſince to be in ſome Company, who, methought, did take a great deal of liberty to ſpeak of you; and indeed their language was ſuch, as I held it more wiſdom to employ my ſelf in a Book which lay by me, than to ſeem to obſerve, or to participate with them. I aſſure you, I minded not the Romance that was before me, but wholly employed my Ears to bring me (if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) what the drift, and what the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was of their Diſcourſe; but inſtead of ſatisfaction, they created in me a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of troubled Thoughts. I had ever an honourable eſteem of your Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and have been ſo great an Admirer of your Perſon, and excelling Beauty, that I have ſuffered (though never known to you) great torment for your ſake. Love indeed did command me to commence my Sute to you; but the near Relation we have to each other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad me: However, I know I did not tranſgreſs, in continuing an innocent Love
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:151469:95"/> and Reſpect to you, and reſolution to ſerve you in what might be in my power to do for you; alſo to vindicate your Honour upon all accounts. Now, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> perhaps you will ſay, Why did you not do ſo now, when you heard me Abuſed and Aſperſed? Your pardon I beſeech you for that. I Anſwer thus: I could moſt willingly have given that Perſon who moſt did villifie you, a Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, and would have been content to have loſt my dear Blood for you, could I have had the happineſs to hear from you how the buſineſs was: For to anſwer Mens Paſſions without the true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ground of all, is raſh and vain. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it will oblige, though not pleaſe you, to have this intimation: and it will oblige me more to hear from you, what might be the occaſion of this. I doubt not but you will deal candidly vvith me, vvhich vvill teach me what I have yet to do. I bluſh to queſtion you; but it vvill be no prejudice for you to Anſwer: therefore do him that Favour, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a few Lines from your Hands, who is, and alwaies muſt be,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Madam,</salute>
                        <signed>Your truly devoted, and moſt humble Servant.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="174" facs="tcp:151469:96"/>
                     <head>The Ladies Anſwer, in which ſhe vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates her ſelf.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Moſt Honoured Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>YOU have done me great Honour in telling me of my Diſhonour. I fear not to give you a full ſatisfaction of what you deſire, but am infinitely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for your diſturbance. What Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he was which was ſo free of his Speech, I preſume will not, nay, I know, dares not affirm to my face. Such pitiful Cowards would be Cudgeld into better Manners: They are not worth a Challenge.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sir,</hi> For thoſe very high Expreſſions you are pleaſed to make of me, I am Conſcious to my ſelf, I never deſerved them, therefore your Obligation is the greater. I have no way to requite it, but to return to you the ſame Reſpect you ſay you have for me. If you dare be conſident that what I ſay is Truth, then believe, <hi>Sir,</hi> I never yet did tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs the bounds of Modeſty. Had I yielded to his baſe Deſign, he had never branded my Honour. I am glad you commanded your Paſſion ſo well as not
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:151469:96"/> to fight: It would have been a laſting Trouble to me, if you ſhould have loſt one drop of Bloud for my ſake. Let me alone with him, I will get ſome ſturdy Porter to Kick him for me. The ſcandal is great: but my Honour will be the greater when the Truth is known. Be pleaſed to do me the favour as to let me ſee you, and then I ſhall more amply give you an account. In the mean time I beg the eſteem of being</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt obliged Kinſwoman, and very humble Servant, <hi>E. N.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Gentlewoman to her Father.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Should be unworthy of ſuch a Father, if I did not by all means poſſible, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to teſtifie my Duty to you, there being a double Obligation upon me ſince my dear Mothers death. Your abſence is my great Grief, and much the greater becauſe you are ſo far diſtant from me. I ſhall pray heartily for the diſpatch of your buſineſs, and for your ſafe return: In the mean time, I ſhall obſerve the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:151469:97"/> Command you gave me. This, with the tender of my humble Duty, is all at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from;</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                        <signed>Your moſt obedient Daughter.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Gentlewoman to her <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle, who had the Charge of her.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Honoured <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>COuld you know how unwilling I am to diſpleaſe you, you would not have ſuch fears when I am from you. I wiſh I could tell how to give you confidence of my Obedience, which I doubt not to teſtifie whenever I ſhall have the happineſs to ſee you; and in relation to that deſire of mine, I ſhall make as quick a diſpatch of my buſineſs as is poſſible, and do not doubt but that you will be fully ſatisfied that I am,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                        <signed>Your moſt affectionate Neece, and humble Servant.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="177" facs="tcp:151469:97"/>
                     <head>From a Widow to her Landlord.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Beſeech your Patience till Thurſday next; when (God willing) I ſhall not fail to wait on you, and bring all that is due. I ſhould have come before now, but that I was diſappointed by thoſe who faithfully promiſed me; and becauſe I would not deceive you any longer, I have craved from a Friend to lend me ſome Mony to make up your ſum: Therefore think not ill of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, but eſteem me</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your honeſt Tenant, and humble Servant.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>From a Gentlewoman of Quality, to her Brother at</hi> Oxford.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Brother,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THe content I have in the thoughts of your moſt pleaſurable life, doth ſomewhat mitigate my Grief for your abſence; yet when I am alone, and have none to condole with me, I hardly know how to ſatisfie my ſelf. If you would be pleaſed to Write to me more frequently, it might much allay my Paſſion, for I ſhould then fancy that I did Converſe with you; nay,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:151469:98"/> and ſee you too; but I fear that your Studies will not admit you ſo much idle time as to think of me long, your Genius being wholly employed to hear the Sage Philoſophers, and the Muſes, which I do imagine cannot chooſe but be very delightful: However, be pleaſed to accept my dear Love and Reſpects, and believe that I am</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt affectionate Siſter.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>From a Gentlewoman, in Anſwer to a Letter from a Gentleman who Courted her.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Received your late Lines, which very much ſurprized me. The Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons you are pleaſed to make, are very far greater than I am able to deſerve. I wiſh you would undeceive your ſelf, and if you have a true Reſpect for me, you muſt alſo be confident, that I will not tell you that which is not Truth. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me then, <hi>Sir,</hi> I have not that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune you hope for, and therefore ſhall not entertain, one thought of giving any Countenance to your Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e. I know it is an ordinary thing, in theſe lave Times, for Gentlemen, when they hear of a
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:151469:98"/> Fortune, preſently to make their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to that Lady, or Gentlewoman, let her be as deformed, or unhandſom a Creature as is imaginable. And, for the moſt part, Women are apt to believe their abominable Flattery, when (God knows) it is their imagined Fortune they Court, and not their Perſon: And for fear any other ſhould rob them of that Felicity they promiſe to themſelves, they huddle up a Match; but when all things come to be made clear, they then begin to think how they ſhall quit themſelves from that wicked Woman who ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them; when indeed they had no reaſon to complain, but of their own Covetous Humour: However he muſt now think of ſome way to advance him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and leave this miſerable Woman to ſhift for her ſelf; and while he yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends great Kindneſs to her, he gathers up all the Mony he can to fit him for his Intentions; and if perchance he have not an opportunity to go out of the Land, but fears therefore to be perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by her, or her Relations, he then proteſts that ſhe was never his lawful Wife; ſo, that unleſs ſhe can bring a Certificate to Teſtifie when and where
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:151469:99"/> ſhe was Married, he quite defeats her; and then is ſhe eſteemed no better than a Whore; others go away beyond Sea, and get employ there, and never think upon the Perſon whom he hath ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly injured, unleſs it be to laugh at her Miſery, and admiring his own Wit in ſerving of her ſo. If Women were of a more Jealous nature, and would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Policy of Men, they might be generally happy; whereas now very few are ſo. I have ſeen and known ſo much, as it hath given me a ſufficient Caution to beware of them.</p>
                     <p>I am not in haſte to Marry. I will take deliberation, and crave Gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and my Friends advice, before I proceed in any ſuch buſineſs: Therefore I do beſeech you not to take it ill, if my Anſwer correſpond not to your deſires, If you have Reſpect for me in that way, I am ſorry for it, becauſe I cannot An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it. I am ſure there is nothing in my Perſon that is attractive, neither is my Fortune worthy one of your Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Eſtate. I have no more to ſay, but that I ſhall be very careful of my ſelf; and if you pleaſe to give your ſelf
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:151469:99"/> no further trouble, but deſiſt, I ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your obliged Friend.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Another Letter from a Gentlewoman, to one who Courted her for his Miſtreſs.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Had ſcarce patience to read your Lines, after I perceived your baſe deſign; but perſwading my ſelf I might the better Anſwer you, I forced a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of my Paſſion from tearing them.</p>
                     <p>Now know, <hi>Sir,</hi> that if you do not make me ſome ſatisfaction for this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable Sute of yours, by asking my pardon before ſome of my Friends, you ſhall receive your due reward for ſuch Villany. If you have a mind to a Whore, there are enough without tempting of honeſt Women from their Husbands. Thus deſiring you to conſider what I have Written, and to have a care of your ſelf for the future, leaſt you meet with ſome Friends of hers</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Who is not yours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:151469:100"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:151469:100"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:151469:101"/>
               <p> I have now done with the Letters, having given you the Forms of as many as may teach you all the reſt, that poſſible you may have occaſion for, and did here intend to have finiſhed my Book; but being unwilling to keep any thing from you, I here preſent you with a very good Receipt, how to make Wax-work; which if you carefully obſerve, it is a very ſufficient Direction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to make Wax-work.</head>
               <p>REd-Lead is for Oranges. When your pure White-wax is melted take it off the fire, then put in ſo much of the fineſt Red-Lead as will make it of an Orange-colour, then wet your Moulds and pour it in; but be ſure that you ſtir it well together to mix it firſt Red-Root is for all Red, for red-Paſte; and that Root muſt be boiled in the Wax a while, till you find the Colour very good. For Pruons, a little Lamb-Black: For Rasberries, Lamb-black and Red-Lead together, ſo much of each as your diſcretion ſhall think fit. Vermil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion for Fleſh-colour: Verdigreace for
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:151469:101"/> Willow-green: and if you put a little Turmerick to it, it will make a perfect Graſs-green; Saffron alſo will do the ſame, and likewiſe Turmerick and Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, or either of them makes a Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-colour; and alſo ſome kinds of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Pears, and yellowiſh Plumbs; which when they are caſt and cold, and taken out of the Moulds, you muſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour them with a Pencil, with ſtreaks and ſpots as you think fit, and with thoſe Colours you think moſt natural for them. You muſt have all your Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours purely ground. Saffron or Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merick will ſerve for any kind of Paſte that ſhould be Yellow, or for Cakes; but then you muſt white the bottoms of them, to make them look like Wafer-ſheets. If you obſerve well the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Work you may take ſeveral Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours from thoſe Rules; and if you would gild any thing of Wax-work, you have already the Rule in this Book punctually given.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:151469:102"/>
               <head>To make the Moulds for the Wax-work.</head>
               <p>Take Plaiſter of Parris, and mix it with Water, and make it like Paſte, as much as will ſerve for half a Mould at a time; for you muſt do no more, becauſe it will dry ſo faſt; then lay it upon a Board, and what you will, have a Mould on upon it, and let it lie till it be dry, when you have done the one half of the Mould, then do the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> That whatſoever you lay upon your Plaiſter of Parris, to make the Mould, muſt be firſt anointed with Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed Oil, or elſe it will ſtick ſo faſt as you can never get it out again; and be ſure to wet your Moulds very well in Water before you pour your Wax into them; and when you have pour'd it in, wave it up and down in your hand, that the Wax may run into every part of the Mould.</p>
               <p>Now for Images; you muſt put every piece in its place, and tie it up, and fill the hollow place full with Water; and then pour it out, and pour in the Wax, and ſhake it about till it be reaſonable cool; then take off the pieces from it, and order it as you think fit,</p>
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:151469:102"/>
               <p> In the ſame manner you muſt ſhake your Sweet-Meats or Fruit, and when you find that it is a little cool, take off the one half of the Mould.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very fine way to make the likeneſs of many ſeveral things in Wax, without the help of a Mould.</head>
               <p>Melt pure White-Wax, and colour it for what you intend it; then take an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range, Lemmon, Apple, Pear, Plumb, or any other Fruit which you fancy, and tie a ſtring to the ſtalk, and anoint your Fruit firſt with pure Sallad Oil, then let it down by the ſtring into the melted Wax, and preſently pull it up again, and hang it on a Line till it be cold; then with a hot knife cut it gently down each ſide, and take out the Fruit within; then heat your Knife again, and hold the two halves together, and cloſe them neatly with your hot Knife, and ſo you have the direct ſhape: You may do ſo with an Egg, if you firſt make a little hole at each end and blow out the meat, and then draw a ſtring through it with a knot at one end. Radiſhes
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:151469:103"/> with their Green-tops look very pretti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Green-Peaſcods, Beans, Walnuts or ſmall Nuts, Cheſnuts, black and white-Puddings, Saucages, Diſhes, little Cups, Plates, or any thing almoſt that you can think of; for there is nothing which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents things more lively than Wax, if they that do it have skill for the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, or elſe it will look as unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To take the ſhape of your own Hand.</head>
               <p>Have your Wax melted, and coloured Fleſh-colour, then dip your Hand as high as you would have it in pure Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lad Oil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or rather anoint your Hand all over with a Feather, and when the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment heat is out of the Wax, dip in your hand, and preſently pull it out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and when it is cold take a hot knife, and cut it in ſuch places as that you may get out your hand, and cloſe it again with a hot knife. Thus you may alſo take the ſhape of your Legs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:151469:103"/>
               <head>For a Dead-body for the Face.</head>
               <p>You muſt anoint it with Oil, and then pour the Wax all over it, and when it is cold take it off, and where you ſee it faulty, mend it with a hot knife: And if you would have the ſhape of the Arms, or of the Legs, you muſt dip them in, as I have ſaid before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Eggs to be hard, and cut in quarters.</head>
               <p>Take an Egg-ſhell, as I have ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and when you have dipped it, and that it be cold, cut it with a hot knife in four quarters, then take the Yolk of a very hard Egg, and preſs it down gently into ſome Plaiſter of Parris, as before, half way; but firſt remember to Oil your Egg: when one half is made, then make the other, and then have melted Wax in a readineſs of the colour of the Yolk of an hard Egg; and then when it is cold, cut it in four quarters and faſten them with a little ſtrong Gum-water to the fore-ſaid Whites. In this Wax-work you may repreſent a Fridays, or Lenten-Dinner, as well as a
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:151469:104"/> Banquet, and both of them would do excellent well; but I would not wiſh to invite a Woman that is with Child to ſee it, for fear of harm. You may, if you pleaſe, mix a little pure Tallow in the melting of your Wax, to make it go the further. When you take the ſhape of any dead Face, you muſt put a little Clay round about by the Hair, to keep the melted Wax from running where you would not have it, elſe it will run very much to waſte. I have known a living Bodies Face taken; but that muſt be with a great deal of Care; the Face being firſt well anointed with pure Oil, the Wax not too hot, the Eyes ſhut, and Clay, as in the other, to keep it off from their Hair; and be ſure you make haſte to make holes for the Mouth and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, for fear you ſtop the breath of the Party; then afterwards you may make the Eyes according to your diſcretion, and colour the Lips with a Pencil, with ſome Vermillion and Gum-water.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe you ſhall be excellent at this Art, I ſhall give you the knowledge of more Colours, and how to make ſome of them your ſelves, which may ſave you ſome Mony. Theſe Directions, with
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:151469:104"/> your own Ingenuity, will make you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Orient Red Colour.</head>
                  <p>SPirit of Salt and Smalt mixed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, makes it of an Orient Red Colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Green.</head>
                  <p>Verdigreace and Argil ground toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make it very well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Yellow.</head>
                  <p>The yellow Chives in white Lillies, Saffron and Argil ground together very fine, make it excellently well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Graſs-Green.</head>
                  <p>The Liver of a Lamprey dried and ground very fine makes a perfect Graſs-Green, and very durable: Alſo Yellow and Blew mixt together make a perfect Graſs-Green.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="190" facs="tcp:151469:105"/>
                  <head>Purple.</head>
                  <p>The juyce of Bilberries mixed with Allom and Galls; and for a Murry take Roſſet.</p>
                  <p>The Berries of Buckthorn gathered green and dried, make a very fair Yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another for Green.</head>
                  <p>Take the Berries of Buckthorn when they are through ripe and black, bruiſe them in a Copper, or Braſs-Veſſel, and ſet it three or four daies in a warm place; then heat it a little upon a fire, and put into it ſome Allom-water; then preſs it forth, and keep it in a Bladder, and hang it up till it be dry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A pure Black.</head>
                  <p>IT is made with the ſmoak of a Torch, held under any thing which is made of Tinn.</p>
                  <p>You may, if you pleaſe, waſh over your Wax-work when it is done, with a little Gum-Arabick Water if you would have them look gloſſie.</p>
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:151469:105"/>
                  <p> Date-Stones well burned upon a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers Hearth makes a pure Black; and ſo doth burnt Harts-Horn, and the Gall of a Neat ground together, and dried in a Shell in ſome ſhady places. Theſe are all very good for Black.</p>
                  <p>Burnt Ivory, or burnt White-bread is alſo good Black.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note,</hi> That the ſmoak of a Torch or link, as I have ſaid, held under a Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Baſen, is that which we call Lamb-black.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For Blew.</head>
                  <p>Take fine Litmoſe, ground with Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe as pale or as deep as you pleaſe, by putting in more or leſs of either of them. Alſo two parts of Ceruſe, and one of Red-Lead doth make a perfect Crane-colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For a Dark Red.</head>
                  <p>Take Turnſoil-Raggs, and let them boil in the Wax for a while, till you find the Colour to your mind.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="192" facs="tcp:151469:106"/>
                  <head>To make Spaniſh-white, which may ſave your Mony; for much of that is uſed in all Houſes generally.</head>
                  <p>Take two parts of fine Chalk, and one part of Allom, grind them with fair-Water till it be thick like Pap; then roul it up into Balls, letting it lie till it be dry; then put it into a clear Fire till it be red-hot; then take it out and let it cool, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I Shall Conclude with ſome Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which I deſire thoſe, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be good Work-women, will take notice of; becauſe whatever they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelves in, they may be able to give an account of, and not work Non-ſence. If they obſerve theſe Directions I give them, they may be able to teach them who are to Draw them.</p>
               <p>I have ſeen ſuch Ridiculous things done in Work, as is an abomination to any Artiſt to behold. As for Example: You may find in ſome Pieces, <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> and many other Perſons of
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:151469:106"/> Old time, Cloathed as they go now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies, and truly ſometimes worſe; for they moſt reſemble the Pictures in Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lads. Let all Ingenious Women have regard, that when they work any Image, to repreſent it aright. Firſt let it be Drawn vvell, and then obſerve the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections which are given by Knowing Men. I do aſſure you, I never durſt work any Scripture-Story vvithout informing my ſelf from the Ground of it; nor any other Story, or ſingle Perſon, without informing my ſelf both of the Viſage and Habit; As followeth:</p>
               <p>If you Work <hi>Jupiter, the Imperial feigned God,</hi> He muſt have long Black-Curled-hair, a Purple Garment trimmed with Gold, and ſitting upon a Golden Throne, with bright yellow Clouds about him.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Mercury, <hi>the Meſſenger of the Gods.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With long Yellow Hair Curled, in a Coat of Flame Colour, with a pure white Mantle, trimmed with Gold and Silver, his Beaver white, and vvhite Feathers like Wings; his Shoes Golden, and his Rod of Silver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="194" facs="tcp:151469:107"/>
                  <head>Apollo, <hi>the Phyſical God.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With long Curled yellow Hair, vvith a Lawrel Wreath, a Purple Robe, a Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Bow, a Golden Harp, and a Throne of Emraulds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Neptune, <hi>the God of the Sea.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With long hoary Hair, a blew or Sea-green Mantle trimmed with Silver, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in a blew Chariot, or upon a Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin of a Brown-black colour, with a Silver Trident in his Right-hand.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pluto, <hi>the God of Riches.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With Black Curl'd Hair, in a Robe of Cloath of Gold.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Bacchus <hi>the God of Wine.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With Curl'd Brown Hair, Cloathed in a Leopards Skin ſpotted, or in a green Mantle, Crown'd with a Wreath of Ivy, or Vine-Branches; his Complexion Taw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Hymen, <hi>the God of Marriage.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With long Yellow Hair, in a Purple or Saffron coloured Mantle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Vulcan, <hi>the Deified Black-Smith.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Let him be Cloathed in a Scarlet-Robe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Genius.</head>
                  <p>In a Purple Mantle, fringed with Gold.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="195" facs="tcp:151469:107"/>
                  <head>Sleep.</head>
                  <p>In a White Mantle caſt over a Black.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cupid.</head>
                  <p>In a Green Robe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Minos, <hi>one of the Judges of Hell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>His Curuſeers to be of Gold, his Robe Blew and Silver, his Buskins of Gold; vvith long Curl'd Brown Hair, and Crown'd with a Golden Crown.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Momus, <hi>the Carping God.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With a Dark-coloured Robe, the hair of his Beard muſt be Party-coloured.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Goddeſſes.</head>
                  <p>Juno, <hi>the Queen of the Goddeſſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>With black Hair, and black Eyes, with a Skie-coloured Mantle wrought vvith Gold and Peacocks Eyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Diana, <hi>the Virgin Goddeſs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With yellow Hair, a Graſs-green mantle trimmed with Silver, Buskins of Silver, a Golden Bow, and a painted Quiver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pallas, <hi>the Goddeſs of Wiſdom.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With a Blow Mantle, embroidered with Silver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="196" facs="tcp:151469:108"/>
                  <head>Venus, <hi>the beautiful Goddeſs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With Gold yellow Hair, attired vvith Black, a Scarlet Robe, and a Dove-colour or Watchet Mantle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Ceres, <hi>the Goddeſs of Corn.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>With yellow Hair, and a Straw-colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured Mantle, trimmed vvith Silver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Tellus, <hi>the Goddeſs of the Earth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In a Green Mantle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Proſerpine, <hi>Queen of Hell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In a black Mantle trimmed vvith Gold flames.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Aurora.</head>
                  <p>In a Purple Robe, and a blew Mantle fringed with Silver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Urania, <hi>one of the Muſes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In a Mantle of Azure, filled with Lamps.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Veſta, <hi>Daughter to</hi> Saturn.</head>
                  <p>In White Garments, filled with Flames.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Aſtrea, <hi>the Goddeſs of Juſtice.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In a Crimſon Mantle, trimmed with Silver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Flora, <hi>the Goddeſs of Flowers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In a Mantle of Divers Colours: And <hi>Night;</hi> In a black Mantle, ſpotted about with Stars of Gold.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="197" facs="tcp:151469:108"/>
                  <head>Ceres, <hi>the Enchantreſs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Her under garment Gold, the ground Green, the Mantle Purple, the three Graces in Silver Robes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Twelve Months of the Year.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>March:</head>
                  <p>Is drawn in Tawny, with a fierce aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, a Helmet upon his head, and lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a Spade, and a Basket of Garden Seeds in his Left hand, and in his Right hand the Sign of <hi>Aries:</hi> And Winged.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>April.</head>
                  <p>A Young Man in Green, with a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of Mirtle, and Hawthorn-Bude; Winged; in one hand Primroſes and violets, in the other the Sign <hi>Taurus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>May.</head>
                  <p>With a ſweet and lovely Countenance, clad in a Robe of White and Green, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered with ſeveral Flowers, upon his Head a garland of all manner of Roſes; on the one hand a Nightingale, in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Lute. His Sign muſt he <hi>Gemini.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>June.</head>
                  <p>In a Mantle of dark Graſs-green, upon his Head a garland of Bents, Kings-Cups, and Maiden-hair; in his Left hand an
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:151469:109"/> Angle, with a box of Cantharides in his Right the Sign <hi>Cancer,</hi> and upon his arms a Basket of ſeaſonable Fruits.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>July.</head>
                  <p>In a Jacket of light Yellow, eating Cherries; with his Face and Boſom Sun-burnt; on his Head a Wreath of Centaury and wild Tyme; a Seith on his ſhoulder, and a Bottle at his girdle: carrying the Sign <hi>Leo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Auguſt.</head>
                  <p>A Young Man of fierce and Cholerick aſpect, in a Flame-coloured Garment; upon his Head a garland of Wheat and Rye, upon his Arm a Basket of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ripe Fruits, at his Belt a Sickle. His Sign <hi>Virgo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>September.</head>
                  <p>A merry and chearful Countenance, in a Purple Robe, upon his Head a Wreath of red and white Grapes, in his Left hand a handful of Oats, withal carrying a Horn of Plenty, full of all manner of ripe-Fruits, in his Right hand the Sign <hi>Libra.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>October.</head>
                  <p>In a Garment of Yellow and Carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon his head a garland of Oak-leaves
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:151469:109"/> with Akorns, in his Right hand the Sign <hi>Scorpio,</hi> in his Left hand a Basket of Medlars, Services, and Cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts; and any other Fruits then in Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>November.</head>
                  <p>In a Garment of Changable Green and Black upon his Head, a garland of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lives with the Fruit in his Left hand, Bunches of Parſnips and Turnips in his Right. His Sign <hi>Sagittarius.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>December.</head>
                  <p>A horrid and fearful aſpect, clad in Iriſh-Rags, or courſe Freez girt unto him, upon his Head three or four Night-Caps, and over them a Turkiſh Turbant; his Noſe red, his Mouth and Beard clog'd with Iſicles, at his back a bundle of Holly, Ivy or Miſletoe, holding in ſur'd Mittens the Sign of <hi>Capricornus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>January.</head>
                  <p>Clad all in White, as the Earth looks with the Snow, blowing his Nails; in his Left Arm a Billet, the Sign <hi>Aquarius</hi> ſtanding by his ſide.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>February.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cloathed in a dark Skie-colour, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in his Right hand the Sign</hi> Piſces.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="200" facs="tcp:151469:110"/>
               <l>LADIES, I hope your pleas'd, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall I,</l>
               <l>If what I've Writ, you may be gainers by:</l>
               <l>If not; it is your fault, it is not mine,</l>
               <l>Your benefit in this I do deſign.</l>
               <l>Much labour and much time it hath me coſt,</l>
               <l>Therefore I beg, let none of it be loſt.</l>
               <l>The Mony you ſhall pay for this my Book,</l>
               <l>You'l not repent of, when in it you look.</l>
               <l>No more at preſent to you I ſhall ſay,</l>
               <l>But wiſh you all the happineſs I may.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>H. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151469:110"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
